<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The counter-plot, or, The close conspiracy of atheism and schism opened and so defeated and the doctrine and duty of evangelical obedience or Christian loyalty thereby asserted / by a real member of this most envy'd as most admired, because, best reformed Protestant Church of England.</title>
            <author>Real member of this most envy'd, as, most admired, because, best reformed Protestant Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6522</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10658</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12534771</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12534771</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62834</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62834)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 311:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The counter-plot, or, The close conspiracy of atheism and schism opened and so defeated and the doctrine and duty of evangelical obedience or Christian loyalty thereby asserted / by a real member of this most envy'd as most admired, because, best reformed Protestant Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Real member of this most envy'd, as, most admired, because, best reformed Protestant Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Atheism --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Schism --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Obedience --  Biblical teaching.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62834:1"/>
            <p>THE COUNTER-PLOT; Or the Cloſe CONSPIRACY OF <hi>Atheiſm and Schiſm</hi> OPENED, and, ſo, DEFEATED; AND THE DOCTRINE and DUTY of Evangelical <hi>Obedience,</hi> or Chriſtian <hi>Loyalty</hi> thereby ASSERTED.</p>
            <p>By a <hi>Real</hi> member of this moſt Envy'd, as, moſt Admired, becauſe, beſt Reformed <hi>Proteſtant CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH of ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>—dabit Deus his quoque finem.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for HENRY BROME, at the <hi>Gun</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. MDCLXXX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62834:2"/>
            <head>The Author to the Reader.</head>
            <p>Error ſhall quit that <hi>Station,</hi> and begin to ſtir and busſle for Room, when we ſee it crouds to the <hi>Chair,</hi> and gapes at the <hi>Cuſhion,</hi> we do then alſo moſt <hi>plainly</hi> ſee, the moſt natural and neceſſary <hi>Tendencies</hi> of ſuch <hi>Emotions,</hi> as ever we <hi>ſenſibly</hi> felt the effects and reſults of them. We <hi>know</hi> as well the certain miſchief and <hi>danger</hi> of ſuch attempted <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments,</hi> as we can remember the <hi>deſtruction</hi> that was brought upon us by their conſequent <hi>Uſurpations;</hi> and we have no more power not to <hi>fear</hi> what we have <hi>felt,</hi> than we have reaſon not to <hi>expect</hi> what we ſo fear, or to deny the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> or the Teſtimonies of <hi>experience,</hi> or to <hi>hope</hi> for any better <hi>concluſion,</hi> becauſe a worſe cannot be drawn, from the ſame Premiſes.</p>
            <p>When we ſee the life of our <hi>Father</hi> in the ſame circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of danger, by which that of our <hi>Grandfather</hi> was firſt <hi>invaded,</hi> and then in common and certain courſe, we know how <hi>deſtroy'd;</hi> can we ſee this without a tongue? or could any thing excuſe us if we did not, but that we could not cry? No certainly, in ſuch a caſe (and I pray God the caſe be not now ſuch) my <hi>fear</hi> to ſpeak would be as <hi>ſinful,</hi> as it would be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious</hi> to forbear. My <hi>guilt</hi> would be as <hi>deep</hi> as my <hi>ſilence;</hi> and the not <hi>proclaiming,</hi> next to that of <hi>procuring</hi> the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; the not diſcovering the <hi>net</hi> and breaking it too if I can, next to the making and ſpreading it if I could: or if I only take the Net away, and make it (and lay it) up, I am ſo far from doing my duty, that I may be juſtly ſuſpected to do againſt it, and by a ſpecious abſtinence from the <hi>appearance,</hi> to go a nearer and ſurer way to the <hi>evil</hi> it ſelf, and under the pretence of prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a preſent (indeed a prevented or uncertain) danger, to aſſure
<pb facs="tcp:62834:2"/>
to my ſelf a better prepared occaſion, for a leſs defeaſable and more certain ruin.</p>
            <p>There is a late <hi>Author</hi> neither unknown nor unlearned, yet more known by a notable <hi>Dedication</hi> of his <hi>laſt</hi> fruits, (as he ſaith, but tells us not how he has diſpos'd of his <hi>firſt</hi>) who has taken great pains, and the greater in reſpect of his age and other infirmities, to dreſs up and prepare a <hi>ground</hi> of <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> &amp;c. wherein truly (how well ſoever he can mean) he does nothing but <hi>actum agere</hi> in either ſenſe, he does that over and over which had been better never done at all; for until he firſt ſuperſedes the neceſſity of putting ſuch a caſe as we have ſuppoſed, till he hath numb'd our ſenſe and experience too of the force of ſuch a ſuppoſal; till he hath parted us from that which is as near as the skin, as concerning as the life, and never to be put off but with our unclothing of fleſh and bloud; till he ſhews us we never had, and that we have not now any ſuch cauſe of <hi>fear,</hi> I ſay 'till he has firſt done all this, his labours will be ſo far loſt, as they cannot appear other or better, than Left-hand Strew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of <hi>green Ruſhes</hi> or dry <hi>Sand,</hi> and to no better uſe or purpoſe than what the <hi>Nurſe</hi> makes of the one, or the <hi>Souldier</hi> of the other, to ſerve only for Coverings of <hi>Filthineſs</hi> or <hi>Deſign.</hi> I wiſh with all my heart (as knowing his abilities) he had rather employ'd his Right hand and Arm <hi>too</hi> with a <hi>Broom</hi> and <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> to have ſwept out the <hi>Nauſeating</hi> filth, and removed thoſe ſcandalous blocks, and that Rock of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> thoſe Blunderbuſſes and Granadoes which we know to be in the <hi>ground,</hi> or under the <hi>ſtrewings,</hi> as well as we know how they came, and who laid them there, or are acquainted with thoſe <hi>love-killing,</hi> and <hi>peace-breaking</hi> (as he calls them) or (as we could better
<pb facs="tcp:62834:3"/>
have underſtood both) thoſe <hi>King-killing</hi> Principles (and Practices too,) which both ſix and ſhew them to be there ſtill; and therefore as (<hi>monſtrum hoc magis horret quod ſub humana ſpecie,</hi> &amp;c.) a Monſter is the more frightful the liker it is a man, we do the more ſuſpect and dread, and ſhun this ground, becauſe notwithſtanding what we know is upon it, yet it ſeems <hi>reaſonably clean</hi> and ſmooth, and ſo fitter for the laying a <hi>net</hi> or <hi>ſcrap,</hi> and alluring the <hi>ſilly bird.</hi> However therefore, as conſidering the Authors perſonal endowments to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his <hi>mixt Practices,</hi> I dare not <hi>affirm</hi> that he intended ill; ſo reflecting the ſame endowments upon his great and notable <hi>experiences,</hi> I know not how to <hi>aſſert</hi> (how much ſoever I am willing to hope) that he meant well.</p>
            <p>But I muſt remember my ſelf accountable to the Reader why I mentioned my Lord <hi>Bacon's</hi> opinion, and every mans duty. It was done purpoſely to give him notice, that I intended the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Sheets a ſmall but good <hi>earneſt</hi> of this <hi>duty,</hi> and a well-meant or wiſhed rather than done or performed <hi>Eſſay</hi> of that <hi>Opinion.</hi> Wherefore I pray they might be ſo accepted only as offer'd thee by thy fellow-ſubject to <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> whom</p>
            <closer>GOD SAVE.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62834:3"/>
            <head>THE Counter-Plot.</head>
            <p>IT hath been well obſerved by Divines from the Language of the Holy Pen-men, that there is ſcarce any one word amongſt them of a more Emphatical and Comprehenſive ſence, than that of Sin, which is therefore Interpreted to us more eſpecially by thoſe ſignal names of <hi>Folly</hi> or imprudence, of <hi>Anomy</hi> or diſobedience, of <hi>Enmity</hi> or ſpightfulneſs; and we are fully inſtructed by theſe notorious Synony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma's, both in the general and common nature of <hi>Sin,</hi> and in the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick and appropriate qualities of <hi>ſinners,</hi> and degrees of <hi>ſinning.</hi> We are plainly taught, as that beſides <hi>this,</hi> there is <hi>properly</hi> no other <hi>evil</hi> in the world, (which the ſence and ſound of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> word [Evil] ſo like in both to that in the Hebrew for <hi>ſin</hi> does alſo evidence) ſo likewiſe that there can be no ſuch fool in <hi>Nature</hi> or <hi>Morality,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> no ſuch Rebel in <hi>Policy,</hi> no ſuch Adverſary in <hi>Religion,</hi> as is the <hi>deliberate</hi> and <hi>deſigning Sinner:</hi> Who if he be not always <hi>actually</hi> (which the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, by the mutual oppoſitions and claſhings of mens luſts, may and doth often hinder,) yet is he always <hi>habitually</hi> all theſe, the ſillyeſt and maddeſt, the moſt diſorderly and ungovernable, the moſt malicious and implacable of all creatures.</p>
            <p>Now the reaſon of this is, becauſe as the folly of ſuch a Sinner lyes not ſo much in the want, as in <hi>refuſing</hi> the <hi>directions</hi> of Wiſdom: ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is his Diſobedience ſo much in his <hi>Nature</hi> as in his <hi>Will,</hi> from whence his Enmity is (Judicially) in both.</p>
            <p>Is not he the raſheſt, and ſo the greateſt fool in the world, that will Bite the ſtone, or Curſe the dice, or Damn the bowls, or Quarrel the government, or whatever hits not his humour; and all this merely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his Paſſion or Intereſt will not ſuffer him to judge of the true nature of things? might we not beg ſuch a Fool as this, and ſucceſsful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too in the judgment of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who throughout his <hi>Proverbs</hi> makes him Impleadable as an Ideot? and yet were not he a worſe than
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62834:4"/>
this greateſt fool, that ſhould take any of this Wiſe mans Materials to lay a Foundation for <hi>Dominion</hi> in <hi>Grace;</hi> an error that we have ſeen built up into an Hereſie, and become a <hi>Fort-Royal</hi> to the Prince of this world; (whoſe beſt Subjects are the worſt of Rebels, and his chiefeſt rule in the hearts of the Diſobedient,) and as tempting a guilded bait for the ſenſe of man, as any we have yet found laid, in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> or <hi>Turkiſh,</hi> or <hi>Malmsbury</hi> Alcorans? I wonder not therefore when I read in the Sacred Oracles, the fouleſt Sins whether of Practice or Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion branded with the name of <hi>folly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet we all know, (if we conſider what we know) that the Devil is no <hi>fool,</hi> it were a repugnancy to his nature, that he ſhould be, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction to our own experience to think him ſo, who is ſo far from that, as he can make us <hi>wiſe to do evil.</hi> And yet the ſinner muſt be a <hi>fool</hi> with a witneſs that learns of him becauſe he is an <hi>Angel</hi> whilſt he knows him to be a Devil,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and not more a <hi>Tempter</hi> in the one, than an <hi>Accuſer</hi> of us in the other, and ſo the true Father of thoſe modern do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, that directly prompt and adviſe me to the greateſt evil of Sin, if it does but ſute with my Inclination, and the deſign of Empire, under the Title of the <hi>Catholick Cauſe.</hi> As great as the fall was, the Devil ſav'd his head, he fell ſo (as we ſay) upon his feet, that he ſtands ever ſince the Archeſt Heretick and Rebel too; in that contrary to his created nature he would not be ſubject to his God, and ſo continues the Enemy to <hi>man now,</hi> becauſe he was that Rebel to <hi>God then.</hi> And thoſe children are likeſt this father who would ſin as unnaturally as he did, and moſt likely to do moſt miſchief for the ſame reaſon.</p>
            <p>The Commands of God in both Tables have ſo like an aſpect, and lay ſuch an equal obligation upon all men, that the violation of <hi>One</hi> makes us guilty of <hi>all,</hi> according to that known rule, <hi>Bonum ex cauſâ integrâ, malum eſt ex quolibet defectu.</hi> Not that there is not a difference in Sins, as there ſhall be in puniſhments (for we read of a greater and leſſer damnation) but that a wilful habitual tranſgreſſion in any one point doth neceſſarily evince the inſincerity of our obedience to all the reſt: in which reſpect it had certainly been <hi>better for us never to have known the Law, than</hi> thus to <hi>tranſgreſs it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The weak and wilful Sinners may be equally miſchievous to others, yet not alike guilty in themſelves; for though both agree in the want of circumſpection and due conſideration, yet they always differ in the meaſure of knowledge, whereby it uſually comes to paſs, that the ſubtle <hi>Serpentine malice</hi> of the one, abuſes the inadvertency of the other, who is therefore ſo much the leſs, as his ſeducer is more guilty, whilſt the one means not the leaſt evil in that ſame thing wherein the other intends the greateſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:62834:4"/>Suppoſe them both Diſſenters from any Publick Eſtabliſhment, whilſt the one <hi>meaſuring himſelf</hi> too much by <hi>himſelf,</hi> and ſo miſtaking Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion for Conſcience, by not ſquaring it ſo exactly as he ſhould by the rule of Conſcience, the Word of God, ſuſpends his Obedience upon the account of his Chriſtian Liberty: The other taking the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of his brothers weakneſs, improves it into the miſchief of his own wilfulneſs, and however he knows <hi>diſtinctly,</hi> that to <hi>deſpiſe domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,</hi> or <hi>ſpeak evil of dignities,</hi> can by no means be any part of that <hi>Liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free,</hi> but that to <hi>ſubmit</hi> to <hi>every Ordinance of man,</hi> is a prime and integral part of that liberty; Though he knows <hi>experimentally,</hi> that Rebellious or Seditious practices never ſail to bring an univerſal hatred and reproach upon the very Profeſſion of ſuch Practitioners; though he knows <hi>confeſſedly</hi> that our Roman-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick enemies (for in that ſence if any, the contradiction of that double adjunct is reconcileable) do ſo continually, as if they did naturally and neceſſarily endeavour, to Deſtroy by dividing, to Divide by amuſing and diſcontenting the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and by this, once already moſt approved and effectual artifice, to make <hi>Proteſtants</hi> themſelves, by the ſtrength and violence of their clamours againſt <hi>Prelacy,</hi> to hale in <hi>Popery;</hi> and that therefore there ſeems no other poſſible way to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent its in road, than by our apteſt methods of Uniting, to defeat theirs of Dividing, for that otherwiſe it would be in vain for us to confute their errors in Doctrine and Worſhip, whilſt we our ſelves commit greater in policy and prudence, by not ſubmitting our ſingle judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the joynt determinations of our Governours: though he knows the <hi>Phariſees</hi> had their name from their ſeparation,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and this had its riſe from their opinion of their own holineſs, or that they were better than other men: though he knows this Proteſtant <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, was and is the <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>hate</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> (and therefore as he knows alſo, not Popiſhly affected, as he (therefore alſo) ſuggeſteth againſt his knowledge) and the <hi>Ornament</hi> and bulwark of all the reſt, and ſtands as the Royal-Fort or Rampire between them and ruin: though he knows what King <hi>James</hi> ſaid, at leaſt he muſt believe what others have ſo lately teſtified,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Oat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Nar. Iſ. Cauſa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. <hi>116.</hi>
               </note> that there are (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>Jeſuites among</hi> us <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (however I cannot deny but it might be hard of digeſtion, for the ſtrongeſt ſtomach and ſharpeſt appetite of Faith, how any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſhould <hi>eo animo,</hi> become <hi>Jeſuite</hi> or <hi>Prieſt, pro hac vice,</hi> to betray both or either, and then <hi>eodem animo</hi> to return <hi>Proteſtant;</hi> or how (upon ſuch ſuppoſal) though he ſtands <hi>(rectus in curiâ)</hi> good Evidence, as we ſay, for the King, or <hi>in foro humano,</hi> how he ſhould ſtand ſo (where yet we are ſure he muſt ſtand or fall) <hi>in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62834:5"/>
foro Poli,</hi> or however he might be rewardable with thoſe things (Riches and Honour) which are <hi>(dignum patellâ operculum) abſolutely</hi> the good things of this world, yet he ſhould be ſo much as <hi>decently,</hi> (I ſay not juſtly) dignified or remunerated with thoſe <hi>(non enim haec filii tunica)</hi> which ſo notoriouſly reſpect another; or how it could acquit ſuch a perſon, becauſe nothing can be ſaid againſt the <hi>man,</hi> whilſt as little can be pleaded for the <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>) Though he remembers at what <hi>Conſults</hi> we were told there was to be, as that ſince there was a <hi>Rebellion</hi> in <hi>Scotland;</hi> ſo though he remembers the Firing of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and the flagitious Atchievements, and moſt nefandous perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>that Parliament,</hi> (did I ſay? I recal that word to vindicate this <hi>Auguſt</hi> and ſalutary name from that <hi>ſink</hi> and draught of the body politick, and ſo better notified to us by its like in the body natural, and therefore, I ſay, not of that <hi>Parliament,</hi> but of that ſame (what do you call it?<note place="margin">The Rump.</note>) <hi>Coccygis mariſcae:</hi>) though he knows, I ſay, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members all theſe things, yet he ſtifles the conſideration of any, claps them all down as it were <hi>under deck</hi> and <hi>holds the truth</hi> in unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and by gradual inſinuations and artificial compliances, as in ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy with the <hi>tenderneſs</hi> impoſes upon the credulity of his brother, and at laſt (which is the greateſt ſhame and affront to humane under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding) menages him into a very tool or engine to ſerve his turn, and makes him thus unwittingly as unwillingly over reacht, a <hi>property</hi> to his luſt, and Tows him from the <hi>ſhoar</hi> of his firſt, and perhaps innocent Scrupling, into the <hi>Main ſea</hi> of <hi>Covenants</hi> and <hi>Aſſociations,</hi> and then as wind or tide pleaſeth, into the bottomleſs <hi>gulph</hi> and endleſs guilt and miſeries of Sedition and Rebellion, Schiſm and Sacriledge, Anarchy and Confuſion.</p>
            <p>All which he moſt compendiouſly effects, by working (as was ſaid) upon his brothers <hi>miſtaken Confidence,</hi> till he has hammer'd it into the <hi>Preſumption,</hi> and then caſt it under the obligation of <hi>regular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> though he knows, as ſoon as he thinks on't, it can be nothing leſs, as being confeſſedly influenc't by ſuch conſiderations as are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther competible to the <hi>nature,</hi> nor conſiſtent with the <hi>rule</hi> of right Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Can that be an obligation of Conſcience which may be cancelled by fear or danger? which makes it my duty to oppoſe that Government to which I am <hi>Naturally</hi> a Subject, and not that to which I am but <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally</hi> or <hi>occaſionally</hi> ſo? which makes me <hi>Fear</hi> my Maſter abroad, but not <hi>Honour my Father</hi> at home? or which makes me deny my Prince and Sovereign that very power which I challenge to my ſelf, that he may not order matters concerning Religion or the Worſhip of God,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:62834:5"/>
at leaſt as well, in his larger, as I may and do, and claim to do in my leſſer Family? How can it be Conſcience, or indeed common Juſtice, that binds me to <hi>one</hi> and not to <hi>both?</hi> Surely if the plea of danger be ſo good againſt the practice, as to evacuate the obligation of <hi>any</hi> neceſſary duty, we may as Logically well, plead other, or leſſer inconveniencies in bar of all. And if cuſtomary or affected Swearing ſhall be as <hi>graceful</hi> as native unaffected Eloquence, if it be <hi>faſhionable</hi> to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, or a <hi>credit</hi> to <hi>riot in the day time</hi> (as God knows by the neighbourhood of ſome viler practiſes theſe are, I am ſure, the leſs, as I fear too little infamous) I need not ſtop from going up to prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon ſuch ſteps as theſe; or if it ſhould be a ſcandal to be Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, I may conſult my advantage or reputation by being otherwiſe, as well as I may think my ſelf bound to innovate Religion eſtabliſht here in <hi>England</hi> where I fear no puniſhment, but loos'd again in <hi>Italy</hi> or <hi>Turky,</hi> where I cannot hope for impunity.</p>
            <p>From theſe hudled premiſſes, as we ſee by the ſtirring of the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings that ſome body muſt be behind them, we are reaſonably excited to the neceſſary uſe of ſo much prudence and caution as may warrant us to <hi>ſuſpect</hi> and <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> our <hi>ſeeming</hi> friends, and to <hi>detect</hi> and <hi>expoſe</hi> if we can our moſt <hi>ſecret</hi> enemies; and that this our ſuſpicion may not it ſelf be ſuſpected, or the detection ſo much as queſtioned, we will now draw back the curtain, and preſent our Caballiſts as in Conſult, and in the very manner, that every man may ſee for himſelf, that (as Naturalliſts report of the <hi>Baſilisk,</hi> that it kills or dyes by ſeeing or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeen) the Conſpiracy thus opened may defeat the Conſpirators, and the very enmity and danger of the Plot, be turned into a ſecurity againſt it ſelf.</p>
            <p>But to clear the proſpect that we may take the fuller view of the <hi>Club</hi> of Monſters, and ſee beſides the <hi>deformity</hi> of their ſingle ſubſiſtences, the greater <hi>uglineſs</hi> of their ſocial Confederate beings, their monſtrous poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Coitions and Copulations, that when looſe and ſingleſt they are <hi>Foxes then,</hi> and miſchievouſly cunning, but when in tayl'd and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin'd, they are <hi>Dragons</hi> too, and fatally pernicious, (the parting of the heads where the bodys are conjoyn'd compleats the Monſter, and however they ran croſs in their premiſſes, yet they never fail (at the old Rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz) to meet in, and draw the firebrand into the knot of the ſame concluſion) I ſay that we may diſcern all this, we ſhall endeavour (as Grammarians deal with their <hi>Anomala</hi>'s, which though fewer in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, give them greater trouble than the whole multitude of regular words) to bring them into particular <hi>Claſſes,</hi> and under a more diſtinct and peculiar conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:62834:6"/>The Enemies of Truth (and by cloſe and neceſſary conſequence, of Peace and Order) we know to be very many, but the chiefeſt of them like all other irregular things fall under one of the extreams, <hi>Exceſs</hi> or <hi>Defect,</hi> and are ſo reducible to Two ſorts, the <hi>Credulous Enthuſiaſt,</hi> and the <hi>Reſolved Infidel;</hi> he that <hi>lightly, weakly, eaſily</hi> believes any thing, and he that <hi>ſeriouſly, wilfully, obſtinately</hi> believes nothing; he that in <hi>Practice</hi> believes <hi>every Spirit,</hi> and he that in <hi>Print</hi> believes none.</p>
            <p>We have liv'd to ſee ſuch <hi>Meteors</hi> in Religion, <hi>Wandring ſtars,</hi> or glaring <hi>Comets.</hi> We have ſeen multitudes of men and women like <hi>empty</hi> clouds exhal'd by the heat of <hi>ſtrange fire</hi> of intemperate Zeal from the turgid miſty Fogs of <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Ignorance,</hi> combin'd in Faction, and then hurried to and again by ſome violent eruptions, iſſuing as it were out of the <hi>Central cavern</hi> of a <hi>Flatulent</hi> Hypochondriack body,<note place="margin">Rumpers.</note> and whirl'd about with perpetual <hi>Agitations</hi> upon the Vertiginous <hi>Axis</hi> of that <hi>Globe;</hi> ſo that whoever he were that firſt gave us notice of a Publick conſtituted <hi>Officer</hi> as properly belonging to ſuch as theſe,<note place="margin">Crack-fart.</note> though in the <hi>Name</hi> he affixeth to this <hi>Officer,</hi> he ſeems not to have been modeſt above the rate or beſides the complexion of his <hi>Sect,</hi> yet in the <hi>thing</hi> or <hi>office</hi> it ſelf, he now appears manifeſtly pertinent and much beyond the intention of his wit.</p>
            <p>We have ſeen Clouds bagg'd with poyſon, fixt and ponderous and <hi>ſpouting</hi> downright upon the bare-heads of the diſciples of <hi>Leviathan,</hi> That Monſter with a witneſs, ſo deſtitute of <hi>right reaſon</hi> as to be void of Religion too. An <hi>Animal</hi> indeed, but ſo far from <hi>Religioſum</hi> (which muſt needs include <hi>Rationale</hi>) that he has only a title (and 'tis pity he ever had that) to <hi>bipes</hi> and <hi>implume.</hi> With <hi>him</hi> it can't only <hi>rain</hi> in <hi>drops</hi> of problem or Opinion, but it muſt <hi>pour</hi> too in <hi>ſpouts</hi> of the moſt daring and impudent affirmations.</p>
            <p>He tells us roundly there is (and for this very good reaſon when it once appears) becauſe there can be no <hi>incorporeal ſubſtance,</hi> for that it would be a contradiction and ſo impoſſible there ſhould be any, as if <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> were nothing akin to <hi>Entity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leviathan p. <hi>214.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to which we all know 'tis nearer allied than to <hi>matter</hi> or <hi>corporeity;</hi> but as we alſo know, they are ſome kind of deformities in our bodies, which make us moſt aſham'd of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſtript,</hi> ſo it muſt be ſome ſuch cauſe that makes us ſo afraid of a <hi>ſeparate exiſtence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I ſhould ſay (as I need not) the diſciple of the <hi>Leviathan</hi> is <hi>mad,</hi> the Reader knows what I mean, and I ſpeak <hi>intelligibly,</hi> or if I ſay he is <hi>beſides himſelf,</hi> I am allowed to ſpeak pertinently, and he, could he <hi>come to himſelf</hi> again, would grant me to ſpeak as <hi>truly,</hi> that he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62834:6"/>
               <hi>was not himſelf,</hi> and that he <hi>was,</hi> when he <hi>was</hi> not ſo; how then can he <hi>confeſs</hi> the leſſer <hi>Separation</hi> which is in <hi>Lunacy,</hi> whilſt he cannot ſo much as conceive that greater <hi>Divorce</hi> which is in <hi>Ecſtacy,</hi> whenas it is manifeſtly repugnant, to <hi>know</hi> any thing in <hi>kind,</hi> which we cannot alſo <hi>apprehend</hi> in <hi>degree,</hi> to <hi>know</hi> any thing to be <hi>actually</hi> at a <hi>leſſer,</hi> which we cannot <hi>imagine</hi> to be <hi>poſſibly</hi> at a greater diſtance.</p>
            <p>So then 'tis not any contradiction in the <hi>terms</hi> of <hi>incorporeal ſubſtance,</hi> that can be the cauſe why there is none ſuch. What then? why truly this or nothing, and this leſs and worſe than nothing, becauſe if there were ſuch a <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> then there muſt be a <hi>Spirit,</hi> (and that would put the hook into this <hi>Leviathan,</hi> for) then there will be a <hi>God,</hi> whereas otherwiſe, (the Monſter were free to take his pleaſure and <hi>paſs time,</hi> for) there could be no <hi>God,</hi> and ſo no <hi>Religion,</hi> and then no good or evil but as forc't and made ſuch by our ſelves. For that ſuppoſing God is or may be, he muſt be <hi>infinite</hi> and <hi>indiviſible,</hi> and therefore alſo muſt be incorporeal, becauſe otherwiſe he muſt have parts, and ſo be <hi>diviſible,</hi> and ſo <hi>finite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diogenes Laertius,</hi> reports of <hi>Pyrrho,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In vita e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus.</note> that he denyed any difference between good and evil (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) other than what Poſitive law or cuſtom had made; and I think <hi>Seneca</hi> tells as much of <hi>Epicurus.</hi> Beſides theſe two I am not preſently aware of any third, till Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> will needs be teaching (<hi>ubi nulla reſpublica,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 72. <hi>de Cive c.</hi> 12. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>nullum injuſtum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>nihil abſolute bonum aut malum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Natura eſt ad man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datum relativa, &amp; omnis actio ſuâ naturâ adiaphora,</hi> &amp;c.) that there's nothing good or evil <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> or <hi>naturally</hi> juſt or unjuſt, but all ſo or ſo in reference to the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> being otherwiſe and in themſelves <hi>indifferent, &amp;c.</hi> But this Gentleman hath forgot, what yet he muſt needs have learnt from one of his great Maſters (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) that there is an <hi>Eternal Law</hi> every way inclining us to that which is juſt and equal;<note place="margin">Ariſtot. de mundo, c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> and that as the <hi>Being</hi> of God muſt needs be <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite</hi> (as we have ſhewn already) ſo muſt it by the like neceſſity of his Nature be <hi>infinitely holy,</hi> becauſe the perfections of God are not Adjuncts but Eſſential to his Nature, wherefore he cannot act but <hi>agreeably</hi> to <hi>them,</hi> he cannot approve or diſapprove any thing but <hi>ſuitably</hi> to <hi>theſe,</hi> ſo that to imagine one thing to be as congruous to him as another, good as evil, muſt needs be Blaſphemy and contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to boot, and make God both to <hi>be</hi> and ceaſe to <hi>be</hi> what he is; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, that God abhors evil, is rather from the <hi>Sanctity</hi> of his <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Eſſence,</hi> than from the <hi>determination</hi> of his <hi>Will,</hi> and therefore whatever is properly and eſſentially good, muſt rather be ſo by its <hi>reſultanco</hi> from this Holy Being, than by any poſitive <hi>Sanction</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:62834:7"/>
or precept of Law; and therefore alſo, 'tis in reſpect of its <hi>Sanctity</hi> rather than <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> that the <hi>Will</hi> of God becomes the <hi>meaſure</hi> of good and evil, which is not ſuch becauſe his <hi>Will</hi> is <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> but becauſe it muſt be <hi>agreeable</hi> to his <hi>Holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though we are not born with <hi>congenit Notions</hi> of good and evil, yet we are born with ſuch <hi>Faculties,</hi> as duely exerciſed between <hi>acts</hi> and <hi>objects</hi> will make us neceſſarily apprehenſive of congruity or incongrui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this or that, whilſt yet this apprehenſion ows it ſelf not only to the <hi>moral,</hi> but to the <hi>connate</hi> and <hi>eſſential rectitude</hi> of thoſe <hi>Faculties,</hi> which ſhew us, by conſideration ſuch a manifeſt <hi>proportion</hi> between ſome, and <hi>diſproportion</hi> between other <hi>acts</hi> and their <hi>objects,</hi> that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repugnancy and doing violence to thoſe <hi>powers,</hi> we cannot judge otherwiſe of them, than that they are <hi>right</hi> or <hi>wrong, equal</hi> or <hi>unequal,</hi> from that proportion or diſproportion, we <hi>thus</hi> perceive in them, and have thereby as certain rational <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Moral</hi> practice, as any we can have of <hi>Science,</hi> and <hi>know</hi> as well that we are to give every one their due, as that two and two make four, and therefore two taken from four leave two ſtill; and thoſe certain determinations which the Soul makes in this rational <hi>exerciſe</hi> of <hi>comparing acts</hi> and <hi>objects,</hi> are thoſe very <hi>iſſues</hi> which Philoſophers call <hi>common Notions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> i. e. the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimental innate,</hi> or <hi>ingrafted Principles</hi> of <hi>Rational nature,</hi> whereby we find our <hi>Intellectual Faculties</hi> to be as much affected with <hi>moral evil</hi> as our <hi>Senſatories</hi> are by the moſt incongruous or ingrateful <hi>Objects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rhet. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.17.</note>Thus we find ſome things, (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> obſerves) <hi>right</hi> or <hi>wrong</hi> by <hi>nature,</hi> or (in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> language) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, juſt or honeſt in the ſight or eſteem of all men, <hi>q. d.</hi> no rational creature can poſſibly eſteem them other than ſuch, becauſe the <hi>faculties</hi> wherewith he judgeth are created by God, who hath made man with ſuch Faculties as make him neceſſarily judge ſo and ſo, and therefore this judgment of his muſt be Gods too, and ſo muſt be a <hi>Law</hi> from <hi>God given</hi> to <hi>man,</hi> which, man as <hi>rational,</hi> cannot depart from, it being the <hi>Law written</hi> in his heart, or wrought into the <hi>eſſential</hi> frame or <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> of his <hi>reaſonable</hi> nature.</p>
            <p>What imaginable account can there be given how the <hi>Gentiles, who had not the Law,</hi> could <hi>be</hi> a <hi>Law</hi> unto <hi>themſelves,</hi> or <hi>do by nature</hi> the <hi>things contained in the Law, &amp;c.</hi> if there were not a <hi>Law in</hi> and <hi>to</hi> that nature <hi>abſtracted</hi> from and <hi>antecedent</hi> to all other <hi>Sanctions</hi> and <hi>Precepts</hi> whatſoever? They had not the <hi>Law written</hi> or <hi>revealed</hi> to them, what Law had they then but this in their nature which was born with them? They could have nothing but that <hi>Natural light,</hi> or the dictates of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62834:7"/>
right <hi>reaſon,</hi> by whoſe conduct notwithſtanding they did thoſe things, which were alſo commanded in the Law of God, or as the Poet words it — <hi>sponte ſuâ ſine lege fidem rectumque colebant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was that <hi>Lex ſcripta in cordibus hominum, quam ne ipſa delet ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitas,</hi> as St. <hi>Auſt.</hi> ſpeaks, that <hi>Law</hi> written in mens hearts which ſin it ſelf could not blot out. This was that <hi>Law</hi> to which a penalty was annext in caſe of Tranſgreſſion, to be taken upon the verdict or teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Conſcience, <hi>i. e.</hi> that reflection the Soul makes,<note place="margin">Conſcience what?</note> and the judgment which by that reflection it paſſes upon it ſelf according to <hi>Law,</hi> without which <hi>Law,</hi> as there could be no <hi>guilt,</hi> ſo without <hi>guilt</hi> there could be no Conſcience. Therefore if the <hi>Law</hi> makes not, diſtinctively, good or evil, we can neither do <hi>well</hi> or <hi>ill,</hi> or have either <hi>comfort</hi> or <hi>regret</hi> in the ſenſe of <hi>one</hi> or <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſcience can never act without reſpect to a <hi>Law,</hi> and to the <hi>Maker</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> of that <hi>Law.</hi> Its <hi>reflexion</hi> would be an uſeleſs and idle thing, if all other things were <hi>indifferent,</hi> becauſe the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of guilt would be <hi>incompoſſible</hi> with the <hi>praecluſion</hi> of <hi>Law;</hi> and therefore every mans <hi>experience</hi> as it <hi>feels</hi> the <hi>one,</hi> ſo it <hi>proves</hi> the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Witneſs the perplexity that haunts the Soul of the moſt cautious and cloſeſt ſinner; Witneſs the laſhes that the <hi>Monarch</hi> feels from the <hi>hand</hi> of Conſcience, though freed from the <hi>touch</hi> of any <hi>other, patitur<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuos mens conſcia manes.</hi> Witneſs the fears and horrors of dying men, who are then moſt afraid of <hi>this</hi> when they are nigheſt out of the reach of all other puniſhment.</p>
            <p>But beſides the teſtimony of Conſcience we have the univerſal conſent of Mankind, there having never yet been any Nation ſo barbarous, that believed every thing <hi>naturally</hi> alike, or that had not ſome <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> too of <hi>Morality.</hi> And indeed were it not thus, were not good and evil made ſuch by nature <hi>diſtinctly,</hi> and <hi>antecedently</hi> to <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws,</hi> theſe <hi>Laws</hi> could ſignifie nothing; for were there no <hi>ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent obligation</hi> to obey thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> Rebellion would preſently be as <hi>lawful</hi> as <hi>obedience</hi> is <hi>neceſſary.</hi> Vain names of Oaths of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> or Promiſes of <hi>Fidelity,</hi> if it be not firſt a duty in it ſelf to keep ones word. I wonder who would then be a Subject, that could hope to better himſelf by being otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Beſides, were it not thus, how ſhould humane <hi>Laws</hi> bind, as we ſee they do, in thoſe places where <hi>Revelation</hi> has not yet been, if the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> to <hi>Obedience</hi> in ſuch places be not reſolv'd into the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> enjoyning Obedience as due to Governours. Yea, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> (I ſpeak now with becoming reverence) how could God himſelf bind us to obedience by any <hi>Poſitive Law?</hi> for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62834:8"/>
unleſs it be firſt my duty to believe God becauſe of his <hi>Veracity,</hi> I am, after the <hi>cleareſt Revelation,</hi> left at my liberty to believe whether the <hi>Law</hi> be from God or no; and if I ſhould be ſo <hi>kind</hi> as to believe him, yet if nothing be good or bad in it ſelf, then to deſpiſe the authority of God cannot be evil, and therefore I may chuſe, as an indifferent thing, whether I will obey him or not. Yea, why may not men if they pleaſe, <hi>invert</hi> the very frame of all <hi>moral</hi> things, and turn Vice into the place of Virtue?</p>
            <p>So abſurd as we have ſeen, is this falſe and dangerous <hi>Hypotheſis;</hi> ſo directly thwart to the firſt <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and to the common ſence of mankind, ſo plainly effective and introductive of all the evil and miſery that can be done or ſuffer'd in the world; that if it could be <hi>reaſonably</hi> believed, that the Author (a man I doubt not eminently Learned) ſhould not be aware of what ſo follows thereupon; it might alſo be <hi>charitably</hi> hop't, that he would have <hi>denyed</hi> himſelf, upon the firſt ſight of ſuch miſchievous <hi>conſequents,</hi> were it not that we ſee many other, and ſome not unlearned, men, who while they <hi>abhor</hi> the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in terms, yet <hi>embrace</hi> thoſe <hi>inferences,</hi> which muſt needs come from them in <hi>courſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tell the <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> there is no God—oh! Abominable that 'tis abominable, and the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> ſhall <hi>feel</hi> his <hi>arm;</hi> but tell him—Kings are not (or obedience due to them is not) Gods, —and you may ſhake his hand.<note place="margin">Suum eui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tribuaere.</note> Tell him there is a <hi>natural</hi> or <hi>original Law</hi> of juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (out upon theſe Atheiſts) he'l ſay ſo too; tell him <hi>right reaſon</hi> is that <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument</hi> by which we <hi>diſcern</hi> this <hi>Law</hi> to be given to our <hi>natures;</hi> ſtill he's content; but tell him that therefore <hi>Obedience</hi> is both <hi>rational</hi> and <hi>natural</hi>— and he begins to ſtart (what do you mean Sir?) Tell him that therefore it is due to <hi>man</hi> as <hi>Governour, i. e.</hi> as the Ordinance of God— you amaze him, (what? <hi>though</hi> he be a <hi>Papiſt</hi>) [where, by the way, <q>we cannot but acknowledge this ſame <hi>though,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Modern Papiſt, or Infidel.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be ſo much the more conſiderable as it carries with it an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> of the loudeſt and harſheſt ſound, <hi>Papiſt,</hi> in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reformed Tranſlation being in a manner the ſame reading with Infidel, or Mahometan; but whilſt I think it the ſevereſt, I may alſo ſuſpect it for the unjuſteſt too, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſuppoſition however made at firſt, God knows, not I; yet ſince that time manifeſtly as enviouſly urg'd and improved by ſome to ſuch a <hi>popular</hi> height, that it now ſeems more than probable they had rather <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> it, though <hi>falſe,</hi> than <hi>truly</hi> not ſuppoſe it, and that they would not quit their advantage, or exchange the pleaſure of <hi>fixing</hi> the <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>odium,</hi> for my <hi>comfort in</hi> or my hope <hi>of,</hi> the improbability of that imputation. Their buſie <hi>floating</hi> upon the <hi>top</hi> or <hi>ſurface</hi> of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62834:8"/>
common fame, will not let them <hi>ſink</hi> to the <hi>depth</hi> and bottom of ſuch <hi>humble</hi> reflexions, as ſuppoſing what they ſuppoſe, would certainly <hi>help</hi> us more, and become us better; for whether is more <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical</hi> think we, the language of <hi>Aſhdod</hi> or the ſpeech of <hi>Canaan?</hi> that <hi>roaring clamour</hi>— he is <hi>Popiſhly</hi> affected, and ſhall never Reign, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or that <hi>ſtill</hi> remorſeful voice— <hi>righteous art thou O Lord, and thy judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are true,</hi> and as we ſin'd by <hi>thruſting out,</hi> as we did, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant King, and <hi>Nurſing Father,</hi> ſo ſhouldſt thou puniſh us, by <hi>bringing</hi> in the contrary, yet ſtill <hi>righteous art thou, O Lord, &amp;c.</hi> But beſides that, we may be jealous of this jealouſie, as ſeeing no more ſufficient ground, than we think they have good cauſe for it, and that we are not to ſuſpect <hi>raſhly</hi> without ſuch ground, or <hi>tumultuouſly</hi> and <hi>irreverently</hi> with it; methinks we have this good reaſon againſt it, that it got no higher than a Suppoſition there, where we doubt not it would, if it could, have been lifted up to an Aſſertion; and I know ſome very near the <hi>ſubject</hi> of this <hi>praedicate,</hi> that know no more of it than I do, and I now thank God, that <hi>thus</hi> I do not know it, and thence may infer my duty not to believe it; my duty I ſay, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe I believe verily <hi>ſuch</hi> a Suppoſition can <hi>hardly</hi> be well made of any man or Chriſtian, without making <hi>another</hi> of the <hi>ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance</hi> or <hi>unſincerity</hi> of the ſame man, nay, it ſeems next to a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction or <hi>moral</hi> impoſſibility that it ſhould be otherwiſe, for how can his <hi>knowledge</hi> admit ſuch doctrines as are pointblank oppoſite to the ſence and reaſon of Mankind? or how can that be <hi>Faith</hi> which em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceth ſuch as are <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>rule</hi> of <hi>Faith?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that the Suppoſition, as firſt made, would fitly ſerve (which can never be thought of without horror) to juſtifie the <hi>Effuſion,</hi> or ſtain the <hi>Innocence,</hi> or elicit an <hi>Ominous Ebullition,</hi> of the yet freſh and pureſt bloud of that <hi>ROYAL MARTYR.</hi>]</q> (But to return from this unacceptable digreſſion,) Tell him therefore the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King muſt be obeyed, whatever he is otherwiſe, and you confound him (away! he cry's, I ſee you are a diſguiſed Proteſtant.)</p>
            <p>Tell another Schiſmatick— God has given us a <hi>Natural</hi> Law, <hi>diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> of good and evil, and ſuch <hi>Faculties,</hi> as duely exercis'd, are ſufficient to <hi>diſcern it, &amp;c.</hi> he readily agrees to the <hi>words,</hi> only he muſt reſerve a <hi>ſence</hi> for his own practice. He is <hi>aſhamed</hi> not to ſay as you do, whilſt <hi>reſolved</hi> never to do what you ſay; and the next news you hear of him, he has <hi>tranſverſt</hi> thoſe very <hi>Faculties,</hi> he is either <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiating</hi> Bodies, or <hi>Gelding</hi> Oaths, or <hi>Depoſing</hi> Kings, or (a ſad pretty thing) <hi>Abſolving</hi> Subjects from the <hi>Law</hi> of their own <hi>Natures,</hi> or, to ſay all in a word, he is <hi>Covenanting</hi> againſt his own <hi>Vows,</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62834:9"/>
ſo <hi>breaking</hi> the <hi>bonds,</hi> blaſting the dignities, and conſuming the perſons of all men and things, <hi>Sacred</hi> or <hi>Civil,</hi> by the breath of that <hi>Fiery-flying-Serpent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Good God! what <hi>Babels</hi> of Opinion and practice does the pride and ignorance of men erect againſt Thee! every man is building like mad, and every man will be a maſter and lay his own foundation. One makes it of the ſmalleſt ſifted particles of <hi>Atomical</hi> duſt, which he found by that ſame good luck, that they had to meet there. Another lays it only with dry looſe ſtones thrown together by the withered and tremulous hands of ſome decrepit and uncertain <hi>Traditions,</hi> doating enough to be thought old, and old enough to be found rotten. Another works it with hewn and ſquar'd and poliſh'd ſtone, but joynted with the moſt untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd mortar of perverſe reaſoning, and vain Philoſophy (a deal of good ſtuff ſpoil'd and worſe than loſt.) Another that ſaith, he ſees the vanity of theſe foundations, yet builds ſuch an irregular Superſtructure, as is only fit to ſtand upon theſe, and worthy for whoſe ſake theſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations themſelves ſhould be razed and overthrown. Such mad work is there made by the luſts and intereſts of men, with the moſt holy Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and laws of God!</p>
            <p>But 'tis well for us, that in theſe <hi>confuſions,</hi> and againſt theſe <hi>extreams,</hi> we are ſufficiently directed and forewarn'd— <hi>not to believe every ſpirit;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1.</note>
therefore we are ſure there are <hi>Spirits,</hi> and that ſome are true, and many are falſe, and all muſt be try'd; and that they may be tryed, we have given us from God the <hi>Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.10.</note> the <hi>gift</hi> of <hi>diſcerning Spirits,</hi> or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing thoſe gliſterings among us, which are not gold, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Commiſſion or Inſpiration of God, for the impulſe or <hi>impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> of luſt; which make good and evil, true and falſe, to be but empty names, or words that ſignifie nothing, or nothing but the <hi>Will</hi> of the Supreme Magiſtrate, and ſo neceſſarily infer this contradiction, that the ſame things in ſeveral places are true and falſe, and our <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> muſt have been a falſe <hi>Prophet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>viathan,</hi> 250.</note> becauſe condemned by the <hi>Roman Governour,</hi> and <hi>Mahomet</hi> a true <hi>Prophet</hi> becauſe allowed by the chief <hi>Sultan;</hi> which teach us that the <hi>Soveraign</hi> power (beyond whatever hath yet been ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated by any <hi>Pope</hi>) may <hi>null</hi> the old,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and make a new <hi>Canon</hi> of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, or none at all.</p>
            <p>Now for theſe, and a thouſand more the like <hi>Spirits</hi> of <hi>error</hi> we may if we will find a plain rule of tryal in the <hi>word</hi> of truth; where we ſee the genuine characteriſtick properties of the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>It is a <hi>Spirit of Truth;</hi> therefore, a good life with an erroneous judgment in <hi>Eſſential</hi> and Fundamental points neceſſary for Faith or Practice, as in the great doctrine of <hi>Obedience to Governours,</hi> which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62834:9"/>
runs through the whole body of the Goſpel, if he allows or abets re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in any caſe; or if he aſcribes <hi>infallibility</hi> to frail and ſinful man; "or priviledgeth a Prieſt to do a greater Miracle than ever Chriſt did, by <hi>Tranſubſtantiating</hi> a piece of bread to make and eat his Saviour; he muſt needs be led by a <hi>Spirit</hi> of error.</p>
            <p>It is a <hi>Spirit of Holineſs;</hi> therefore, to be Orthodox and yet immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, to have good opinions with bad practices, to <hi>think</hi> right, and to <hi>do</hi> wrong; is to be led by the <hi>unclean ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a <hi>Spirit of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> therefore, to <hi>Reform</hi> by <hi>Schiſm,</hi> to diſſolve the <hi>Bond of Peace,</hi> wherein the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit</hi> is to be preſerv'd, to ſeparate or Abſolve Subjects from their Obedience, to teach them to ſwear, to be forſworn, or to lye for Gods ſake, is to be led by the <hi>Spirit of diviſion,</hi> whoſe name is <hi>Legion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a <hi>Spirit of meekneſs and order;</hi> therefore, to <hi>deſpiſe dominions,</hi> to excommunicate Kings, or ſubvert Kingdoms, is to be led by the <hi>Spirit Abaddon</hi> or <hi>Apollyon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11.</note> the <hi>Spirit</hi> of miſchief or deſtruction always <hi>working in the children of diſobedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a <hi>Spirit of Sincerity,</hi> working in us ſimplicity and ſingleneſs of heart; therefore to lift up the Left hand to God, and the Right againſt his Vice-gerent; to hate Idols, and love Sacriledge; to declaim againſt the <hi>Prelacy</hi> of Conforming, and Vote up the <hi>Papacy</hi> of Nonconform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſters, is to be acted by the <hi>Spirit of Hypocriſie,</hi> or the father of Lyes.</p>
            <p>It is a <hi>Spirit of Knowledge</hi> or underſtanding; therefore, to level the <hi>Canon</hi> of Scripture with the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> to make the Word of God truckle under <hi>Tradition;</hi> to advance <hi>Jeſus</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſt;</hi> or to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate Religion by the Sword, is to be led by the <hi>Spirit of Slumber,</hi> the <hi>God of this world</hi> that blindeth the minds of men.</p>
            <p>Thus let us <hi>Try the Spirits,</hi> and <hi>by the fruits of Love, Joy, Peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.22.19.</note>
               <hi>Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs. &amp;c.</hi> or of <hi>hatred, variance, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, hereſies, &amp;c. we ſhall</hi> eaſily <hi>know them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet becauſe Vice borders cloſe upon Vertue, and is never without ſome colour or probability to ſet it off, we are not to make our laſt judgment upon the <hi>Acts,</hi> till we be firſt acquainted with the <hi>habits</hi> of men: till we know the general <hi>current</hi> of their lives, as well as the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>conduct</hi> of their deſigns, and the <hi>means</hi> they uſe as well as the <hi>end</hi> they pretend to; and when this is done, let the <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>godlineſs</hi> be never ſo artificially drawn, the fire of <hi>Zeal</hi> and the light of <hi>Sanctity</hi> never ſo well painted, let the Colours be never ſo fine ground, and laid on with never ſo delicate a Pencil, we ſhall ſee the difference between the Picture and the Life, and though the <hi>grapes</hi> ſhould be lively enough
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62834:10"/>
to deceive the Birds, the <hi>Boy</hi> will be dead enough to betray the cheat.</p>
            <p>The firſt <hi>Impoſtors</hi> that ever appeared in the Church of Chriſt (and ſuch there did appear even in the moſt Primitive and pureſt times) were <hi>brave fellows</hi> indeed, ſuch as had not our modern baffl'd thread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare canting <hi>forms,</hi> but ſpan new and freſh-napt <hi>ſigns</hi> of <hi>godlineſs</hi> and <hi>wonders</hi> too; ſuch as might have credited the ſofteſt <hi>credulity,</hi> to take up pity any where.<note place="margin">Barcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaebus. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollonius. Sim. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus.</note> One could vomit flames; (but may not the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of Sedition vye with him?) Another had the knack of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biquity,</hi> and could tell at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> what was done at <hi>Rome</hi> (I doubt that's far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>) Another could fly (but could not one of our Aiery <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> with the advantage of his <hi>light</hi> (for he muſt mean levity of judgment) <hi>within him,</hi> do at leaſt as much? I think one might adviſedly wager on this ſide whether for <hi>towre</hi> or <hi>ſtretch.</hi>) Yet theſe would ſcarcely be good juglers at this day; 'tis plain they have been all out-done both with and without the <hi>Metaphor.</hi> We have thoſe who from their Seditious ſanguinary Principles, do naturally (ſure that's as much as literally) ſpit fire and bloud together; yet can no more <hi>speak with tongues,</hi> than they can <hi>vomit flames</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>Metaphor,</hi> or more honeſtly pretend to learning, than they can to flying; or to know what is done by others, than to conſider what they do themſelves. They pretend as little to the <hi>gift</hi> of <hi>obedience,</hi> as to that of <hi>Tongues</hi> or <hi>Healing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Kings and Biſhops.</note> and are therefore probably the leſs pleas'd with thoſe, who either <hi>exact</hi> the one, or <hi>exerciſe</hi> the other.</p>
            <p>Generally I ſay they do not ſo much as pretend to Learning; no, their provident Father fitting their ſtocks to their trade, and their <hi>wiſdom</hi> to their <hi>generation,</hi> has furniſht them with much induſtry and little wit, ſo little as to lay that claim which they have quitted to Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to the <hi>gift</hi> of <hi>Preaching,</hi> (to ſay nothing yet of the <hi>gift of Prayer</hi> till we ſee a little farther, whether they underſtand what it means) wherein yet every body knows they exceed in nothing more than noiſe, though we may not deny, that they temper that exceſs with as great a defect of ſence. But admitting that they Preach'd eminently well (which many think 'tis plain they do not) I hope the Heretick <hi>Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> went beyond them; and though they equall'd him, yet if he, or they, or an <hi>Angel from Heaven,</hi> ſhould Preach another doctrine than what hath hitherto been deliver'd, to lead us into <hi>Rebellion</hi> or <hi>Schiſm,</hi> or <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> we could give them no better entertainment than that of <hi>Anathema Maranatha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Numa. Eumenes. Mahomet. Ilaricus.</note>If they pretend to immediate Revelations, for their comfort they are not alone, we can bring them a <hi>Roman,</hi> a <hi>Greek,</hi> a <hi>Saracen,</hi> a <hi>Goth</hi> to bear
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62834:10"/>
them company. Or ſuppoſing they had a ſleight of hand (as in <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions,</hi> and ſome ſuch caſes muſt be acknowledg'd) yet <hi>Apollonius Tyanaeus</hi> could have put them down. If they plead Proſperity or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity in Sin as an Argument of Divine Approbation, we ſay from the Word of God, that this is one of the wickedeſt ways of reaſoning, and we add for their inſtruction or encouragement, it is that very way wherein the <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> of <hi>ROME</hi> have moſt delighted. Alas! how patiently did God permit the diſobedience of the firſt, and the murther of the ſecond <hi>Adam?</hi> yea and all the villanies of the world, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever moſt contrary to the Precepts, are yet executed by the permiſſion of God. If Piety ceaſeth to be ſuch, becauſe proſperous, or permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or not hindred by force (inconſiſtent with a free and <hi>moral</hi> Agent) then the great <hi>Mogul,</hi> or the greater Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhould now be as great Favourites of Heaven (and ſo I think they are) as ever our <hi>Regicides</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> were; and he that having robb'd the Temple of <hi>Delphos,</hi> immediately after eſcap't a ſhipwrack, had ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued <hi>Logically</hi> well, in concluding as he did, from that deliverance, that the gods had approved his Sacriledge.</p>
            <p>Do they live ſtrict and Religious lives, yet in Schiſm and Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bience to the Ordinances of God? (for ſuch are humane Laws) we ſay 'tis impoſſible they ſhould do ſo, becauſe 'twere a contradiction, and yet that though they did ſo, it would not be argumentative, becauſe we have heard from St. <hi>Jerome</hi> of the abſtinence and <hi>Scleragogy</hi> of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus,</hi> that his ſtrictneſs was his diſeaſe,<note place="margin">Hieron. ad Marcel.</note> and from no better <hi>Spirit</hi> than his <hi>Spleen;</hi> and therefore they are not to be blam'd that cannot ſo readily and roundly <hi>Saint</hi> a <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> becauſe he is no <hi>drunkard, ſwearer, ſabbath-breaker,</hi> or <hi>adulterer,</hi> for that theſe though all damning ſins, are yet leſs intolerable than <hi>Envy, Malice, Schiſm, Sacriledge, Hypocriſie,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> or that moſt <hi>intoxicating</hi> ſin of <hi>Spiritual pride,</hi> which are ſo properly the Devils ſins (as drunkenneſs and whoredom can never be) that they are called <hi>deviliſh</hi> whereever they are found in men, and are in St. <hi>Peters</hi> judgment,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9, 10.</note> the moſt damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Do they refuſe our Aſſemblies becauſe they hate them, and do they hate them becauſe our Worſhip is either meerly <hi>Technical</hi> and <hi>Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical</hi> as the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> drolls out his bolts, or plainly Idolatrous and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, as the <hi>Schiſmatick ſhoots his arrows?</hi> But is it indeed, or can you think it is either ſo, or ſo? Speak out ye ſons of <hi>Anak</hi> or <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan,</hi> is our <hi>Liturgy</hi> ſuch a <hi>Pageantry</hi> of Worſhip? a knack or trade invented by Prieſts for filthy lucres ſake, and by them accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the priviledge of <hi>Inventers</hi> monopoliz'd? This is Gyant-like, a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62834:11"/>
right <hi>faller on,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nephilim.</note> and faller off from God, he ſpeaks congruouſly to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf big and high and terrible; and if there be no God he ſpeaks wiſely, he is no fool. For what buſineſs hath he to do with that <hi>name,</hi> or what reaſon to take it into his mouth (other than to ſpit it out in droll) whoſe <hi>being</hi> is not in his heart? What's he concern'd in <hi>Liturgick</hi> or <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſticks</hi> that has nothing to pray to or for, no God to <hi>praiſe</hi> or <hi>honor</hi> with the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of his <hi>lips?</hi> But if there be a God, then the <hi>fool</hi> turns back with triumph upon the <hi>man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rephaim.</note> and the Babe upon the <hi>Gyant,</hi> and the <hi>antiphraſis</hi> is utterly reverſt, and he languid and feeble, and faint and weak, without the <hi>Metonymy;</hi> ſee this <hi>Infant-Gyant</hi> who is not now ſo much as that <hi>ſpan</hi> long, which before he exceeded by <hi>Six cubits!</hi> ſee this fierce, ſwift, bold, terrible and mighty <hi>Leviathan,</hi> an impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and fearful <hi>Minim!</hi> ſee yet a ſtep lower, this living and roaring <hi>Lyon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 26.5.</note> a dead Carrion dog, degraded as low as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or inanimate, <hi>fallen</hi> down to a <hi>dead thing.</hi> Yea, a (<hi>Mappeleth,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>cadaver</hi>) dead carkaſs, for ſuch the <hi>vulgar latin</hi> makes this <hi>Gyant.</hi> And now the fool peeps again, not only the raſh, bold, furious, inconſiderate, but the very <hi>natural</hi> (indeed moſt <hi>unnatural</hi>) fool. The <hi>Virgins</hi> that had no <hi>oyl,</hi> were manifeſtly akin to this <hi>fool,</hi> by their ſupine negligence and improvidence, yet not nearer ſure than the <hi>half bloud</hi> of groſs and woful imprudence, not the <hi>whole</hi> of ſtark ſtaring madneſs. Thoſe fools would have beg'd or borrow'd what they had not; this fool will not ſo much as need what he wants. He hath, he will have, no <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for God, which even the Heathen themſelves have always made to be the <hi>due</hi> and neceſſary acknowledgment of a <hi>Deity.</hi> But let us <hi>bray</hi> this fool no longer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy not corrupted by the Miſſal.</note>Say <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> what is our Liturgy? Oh! moſt abominable, filthy, noxious, childiſh, confuſed, tedious, improper, literal, Book-ſervice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> a moſt blind, lame, yea a dead Sacrifice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hold a little, is it all this? yet, methinks, if it be a Sacrifice of Praiſe to God, it matters not through what hands it paſt e're it came to us. What can the <hi>Miſſal,</hi> (if it were the <hi>Alcoran</hi>) of <hi>Rome</hi> concern us or defile it? We ſay of our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> juſt as we do of our Religion, it is not <hi>New</hi> but <hi>Reformed.</hi> What ails you now? unleſs you love <hi>Schiſm</hi> for it ſelf, it ſhould offend you no more than it troubles us that our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> are all of a piece.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment to the Spirit of Prayer. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26.</note>Nor can ſet and ſtinted Forms, as ſuch, poſſibly in any degree <hi>quench</hi> or hinder the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Prayer,</hi> for that as this is not ty'd to or with words, ſo neither doth it ſupply any defect in them. It <hi>helpeth our infirmities</hi> indeed, but not with words, but with ſupplies that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be worded, <hi>with</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>ſighs and groans unutterable.</hi> It conſiſts
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62834:11"/>
in thoſe <hi>fervours</hi> of Soul that will put life into any <hi>Form,</hi> not in <hi>forms</hi> of my own making or borrowing, as you lamentably affirm, and ſo cheat the people, and <hi>(eadem opera)</hi> blaſpheme the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>You complain of eaſe, whilſt you tell us a child might perform this Service, for that is both our advantage and obligation,<note place="margin">Not child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh becauſe a child can read it.</note> Gods Service being not to be weighed by the labour of doing, but by its relation to him for whom 'tis done, elſe we know a Butcher could have kill'd and dreſt a <hi>Lamb</hi> better than a <hi>Prieſt</hi> under the <hi>Law,</hi> and now the child that can read the book is not therefore fit to offer the Sacrifice under the Goſpel. He can read— Take, eat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but may he therefore Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You could never be ſo much troubled with our confuſed <hi>Antipho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's,</hi> if your <hi>Ears</hi> were not as tender as your <hi>Conſciences,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Antipho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na's</hi> no Confuſions</note> for I pray tell us, is it not a publick <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> a joynt <hi>Confeſſion</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) which (for ought we know yet) muſt be made by Speech, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we pray God to <hi>open our lips,</hi> and you teach the people to ſhut them: Is <hi>this</hi> well done, or is not <hi>that</hi> better?</p>
            <p>Neither could you think it <hi>impertinent,</hi> if you conſidered it to be a publick <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Praiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice not imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent,</note> not only for Bleſſings immediately upon our ſelves, but upon others, or upon us by the means or <hi>intervention</hi> of others. Might not you, may not we partake of the Grace vouchſaf'd to the <hi>Bleſſed Virgin,</hi> in her <hi>Magnificat?</hi> or may we not all with <hi>Simeon,</hi> in his Song, rejoyce at the <hi>ſight</hi> of that <hi>Salvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So 'tis much any man ſhould think thoſe Prayers too long,<note place="margin">not tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,</note> wherein we are begging for <hi>Eternity,</hi> or quarrel them for juſtling out Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which as they do not <hi>neceſſarily,</hi> ſo if they do it <hi>accidentally</hi> or by ſurprize of ſome occaſion, yet then, which do you think may better be ſpared, the <hi>Prayers</hi> which are (a <hi>Sacrifice</hi>) to God and for his <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> or the <hi>Sermons</hi> which are to us and for our <hi>benefit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how is it that you call it a <hi>dead Sacrifice?</hi> what?<note place="margin">not a dead Sacrifice.</note> does it want that life of <hi>affection</hi> which is neceſſary? Truly this muſt be a fault, lay it where it may; but can the <hi>Forms</hi> be guilty? can we <hi>juſtly</hi> require that in or of the <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> which only belongs to them that offer it? muſt the <hi>Church</hi> create the <hi>affection,</hi> becauſe ſhe compos'd the <hi>Forms?</hi> If we come without our hearts, is not the fault our own? can <hi>Repetition</hi> deaden Affection? or cannot our ſenſe of the <hi>ſame</hi> wants, or can words ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and not the <hi>ſame</hi> keep life in it? did the <hi>Jews</hi> ever complain of their Sacrifice (the Type of ours,) becauſe there was a <hi>Lamb</hi> in the Morning, a <hi>Lamb</hi> in the Evening, a <hi>Lamb</hi> every day in the year?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> did our Lord think you, want <hi>ability,</hi> or <hi>affection</hi> to pray, when he <hi>thrice</hi> uſed the ſame words?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62834:12"/>
               <note place="margin">Nor lame.</note>How is it defective or lame in its parts, its <hi>Confeſſions, Petitions,</hi> or <hi>Thanksgivings?</hi> Is not the end and uſe of it to be a <hi>Sacrifice of Praiſe,</hi> rather than a ſtorehouſe for every duty, otherwiſe than to ſerve for that <hi>Sacrifice?</hi> why do you not conſider, that if <hi>particulars</hi> were <hi>named,</hi> all could not ſay <hi>Amen?</hi> And when <hi>general</hi> words are uſed, all that are acquainted with their own Souls can reflect upon particulars, and ſo make a private advantage of the publick ſervice.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Nor blind.</note>How is it blind, or not edifying? Is it becauſe it edifies us not in Faith or Knowledge, as a <hi>Sermon</hi> doth, or ſhould? why then it ſeems it is to be blamed becauſe it is not a <hi>Sermon.</hi> But how then ſhall <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> eſcape, becauſe they are not <hi>Prayers,</hi> nor a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> for the <hi>praiſe</hi> of God, as this is? And now I hope well, that if this <hi>edifies,</hi> it will be enough to ſuperſede the complaint.</p>
            <p>Tell us therefore, do not <hi>Hymns</hi> and <hi>Anthems</hi> with Muſick too, edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the <hi>Praiſe</hi> of God, even in Chriſtian worſhip? diſprove it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue an enemy, or grant it, and become a friend to this Holy Service. Never be ſo bold hereafter as to dare to ſay—there's nothing but (por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge) <hi>Prayers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 69.30.71.20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or if thou wilt, remember thou ſaiſt alſo— there's nothing but <hi>Honouring</hi> or <hi>Praiſing</hi> God. Conſider likewiſe thy <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> is a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> but it is not <hi>this Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Praiſe;</hi> that's a <hi>metaphorical,</hi> but this is a <hi>proper Sacrifice.</hi> For though that word [Sacrifice] imports ſomething to be ſlain or deſtroyed, yet that is but accidental to its notion,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and rather diſtinguiſhes the <hi>kind,</hi> than conſtitutes the <hi>nature</hi> of it, which conſiſts in offering ſomething to God in acknowledgment of him, and which is as properly done <hi>now</hi> by the <hi>fruit</hi> of our <hi>lips,</hi> as of our <hi>flocks</hi> or our <hi>fields</hi> before. Therefore we <hi>rob</hi> God, if we deny him the <hi>honour</hi> of this <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> which as it is diſtinct from all other acts of <hi>obedience,</hi> ſo is it of a ſpecial intendment, and of a different obligation, though he hath alſo from us the <hi>honour</hi> of obedience, becauſe this is only of conſequence, as agreeing with the <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>will</hi> of God. Say now again, is our <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Service Idolatrous,</hi> or <hi>Superſtitious?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh ye bleſsful <hi>Souls</hi> of <hi>Cranmer, Ridley, Hooper, Latimer, &amp;c.</hi> are not we followers of you, or were not you of Chriſt! Is our Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more or leſs than yours? Tell us if it were not part of your <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph,</hi> that you enjoyed thoſe very priviledges which the preſent eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment affords us! 'Tis true, there were ſome differences of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment even among theſe: but not more I trow, nor greater than were between St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> nor of worſe conſequence among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (however ſince perverted by Poſterity) than theirs were. They had not all the ſame mind in all things, but they had all no mind to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62834:12"/>
They were men, but good men, ſincere men, therefore differing and therefore not divided. They had ſeveral opinions of ſome <hi>leſſer circumſtantial</hi> things, but gave them all up (and at ſuch a time as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience muſt needs have been moſt awake) to thoſe <hi>greater</hi> and <hi>eſſential</hi> intereſts of <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>unity.</hi> The moſt fearful among them did but <hi>ſlacken</hi> their ſteps thoughtfully, none of them ſtood ſtill <hi>reſtively,</hi> or ſtubbornly, or ſtayed till the <hi>Government</hi> ſhould <hi>come</hi> to them by <hi>Tele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> rather than they would <hi>go</hi> to it by <hi>Conformity.</hi> No, no, they knew for all the prejudices of Foreign converſation, or domeſtick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, either of which might have been apt enough to drive them out of, or beyond their pace, they knew well how <hi>Obedience was better than Sacrifice,</hi> but knew nothing of our modern <hi>Gloſs,</hi> which ſacrifices <hi>obedience</hi> it ſelf to the <hi>Mammons</hi> of intereſt or humour.</p>
            <p>How unlike were their peaceable <hi>Diſſentings</hi> to our Seditious <hi>diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions!</hi> Thoſe ſoft and tender <hi>Willows</hi> to our hard and ſturdy <hi>(Ket's) Oaks</hi> of <hi>Reformation!</hi> quite another thing in their cauſes and effects, their means and ends, their extraction and converſation. Their differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were neither begotten of <hi>Pride,</hi> nor born of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> but the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful iſſue of godly <hi>jealouſie</hi> and humble <hi>fear;</hi> ſo born in honeſt wedlock, Chriſtned by the <hi>Canon</hi> of <hi>Scripture,</hi> atteſted by the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> proclaimed and certified to us, as with Drum and Trumpet, by their Noble Army of Martyrs and fellow-ſouldiers. They were not menaged by peeviſh publick <hi>Remonſtrances,</hi> or (the ſame thing in other words) <hi>prohibited Petitions,</hi> but by modeſt inquiries, by private gentle diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, by fraternal correptions or admonitions, and at laſt ſweetly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded (and indeed neceſſarily from ſuch Chriſtian premiſſes) in moſt <hi>Evangelical</hi> complyances and condeſcenſions.</p>
            <p>There have been, there are, there will be differences in the <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> till there be none in the <hi>faces</hi> of men,<note place="margin">Schiſm.</note> only let them be without <hi>offences,</hi> however without that which has more than all the reſt, and is the <hi>Rock of offence, SCHISM.</hi> An offence with a witneſs, having as much of the <hi>Devil</hi> for it, as of Chriſt againſt it: A difference as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian</hi> as <hi>Inhumane,</hi> not only of <hi>intereſts</hi> but of <hi>natures,</hi> making one man a <hi>Wolf</hi> (in Plundering,) a <hi>Serpent</hi> (in Trapanning or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plotting,) and a <hi>Devil</hi> (in accuſing) to another. For my own part as I doubt not there are many, ſo I am perſwaded that I know ſome in the preſent Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſo abhorrent from any likeneſs or appearance of Superſtition, that they are always ready <hi>(in voto)</hi> to interpoſe their own lives between it and their Conſciences, who yet chuſe to incorporate themſelves into this Eſtabliſht body, as the apteſt, the cleareſt, the ſureſt evidence of that abhorrence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62834:13"/>This <hi>Clouds</hi> of <hi>Witneſſes</hi> paſt away before our memories, only by the <hi>hearing of the ear,</hi> but there's another which <hi>our eyes have ſeen,</hi> (though no bigger at firſt than a mans hand,<note place="margin">Arch-Bp. <hi>Laud.</hi>
               </note> or the dimenſions of a ſingle perſon, yet quickly ſpreading it ſelf over the ſurface, and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Horizon</hi> of three Nations, with ſuch a thick and palpable darkneſs, as will never let us forget how long it was ere <hi>Sun</hi> or <hi>Stars</hi> appeared.) A <hi>Martyr</hi> of the infelicity of the times he liv'd in; A <hi>Martyr</hi> againſt the <hi>Devil</hi> (and his principal work) of <hi>Schiſm;</hi> and how then, or who ſays, not a <hi>Martyr</hi> for the God of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity?</hi> who wrote himſelf ſo <hi>Legibly</hi> a Proteſtant, that even (that which we know runs faſteſt from truth) prejudice it ſelf, or any thing but groſs or affected ignorance may read it; ſo that one might with as much truth and reaſon deny him the name of his <hi>firſt</hi> Baptiſm <hi>(Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Laud)</hi> as with juſtice or good manners, that of his <hi>ſecond, Proteſtant Martyr,</hi> a Name ſo truly and eminently his own, that beſides his <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> by purchaſe (as before) he has that of <hi>Royal donation,</hi> and that alſo from that Firſt <hi>CHARLES,</hi> THE PRINCE OF PROTE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STANTS AND MARTYRS TOO; wherefore it may be good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, or caution to him that thinks or ſpeaks otherwiſe, to conſider well, whether he can reaſonably ſuppoſe, there were any man then living, with ſo great advantage to know, or ability to judge, the mind and cauſe of that happy man, that unhappy <hi>Metropolitan,</hi> as was that incomparably moſt Judicious <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to reſume our buiſineſs of inquiry; does the Schiſmatick diſlike our Worſhip becauſe he likes not our <hi>Diſcipline?</hi> Is he offended at that lenity and <hi>longanimity</hi> which is uſed towards ſcandalous ſinners? If this be it, then let them firſt compare (as was noted before) thoſe ſins which the Devil never commits, with thoſe which are proper to him, and then religiouſly conſider the dreadful <hi>Emphaſis</hi> of St. <hi>Peters</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>chiefly</hi> or <hi>eſpecially</hi> concerning thoſe that <hi>deſpiſe Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> of whom he tells us that they are <hi>eſpecially reſerv'd by the Lord to the day of judgment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>to be puniſhed;</hi> and then though our Miniſters do not (what they cannot lawfully) ſhut the doors againſt ſuch ſinners till excommunicated, they will either think with more Charity of our <hi>Communion</hi> or with leſs <hi>Arrogancy</hi> of their own, and ſeparate from us, if at all, with the temper and language of that meek <hi>Centurion (Domine non ſum dignus) Lord I am not worthy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 7.6. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ</hi> 65.25.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not of thoſe Idolaters in the Prophet— <hi>ſtand further off, &amp;c.</hi> And then how would ſuch an exceſs of <hi>humility</hi> in them, be quickly matcht with another of <hi>Charity</hi> (with arms and hearts!) from us! what <hi>joy</hi> would there be in <hi>heaven,</hi> what <hi>peace</hi> on <hi>earth,</hi> what harmony in both! How
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62834:13"/>
would the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> bluſh, the Papiſt fret, and our Schiſmatick leer, and all the enemies of God and the King <hi>be as that young man Abſalom!</hi> Whereas on the contrary, if theſe brethren of ours (Alas! our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren! for ſuch they profeſs <hi>frequently</hi> they are, and ſuch God knows we deſire moſt <hi>paſſionately</hi> they ſhould be) will ſtill remain inexorable by all the methods of reaſon or loving kindneſs; if they will invincibly perſiſt to maintain their ſeparation, to deprave the <hi>doctrine,</hi> diſturb the <hi>diſcipline,</hi> and diſown the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church; if they will <hi>walk</hi> thus <hi>diſorderly,</hi> in contempt of all authority and publick order; we muſt then, (whether we would or no, for Chriſt has made it our duty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 18.17. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11.</note>
and re-inforc't it upon us by St. <hi>Paul</hi>) we muſt then I ſay, deal with all ſuch as the <hi>Jews</hi> did with <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Publicans,</hi> we muſt <hi>withdraw</hi> from them in their <hi>diſorders,</hi> and in caſe of irreclaimable contumacy, not only not <hi>religiouſly,</hi> but not ſo much as <hi>civilly</hi> entertain them, or as St. <hi>John</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>we muſt not receive them into our houſes, or bid them God ſpeed.</hi> And indeed what reaſon can there be that we ſhould eat or drink with them at their or our own <hi>Table,</hi> who are therefore too unworthy, becauſe they think themſelves too good, to eat or drink with us at the <hi>Lords Table!</hi> Or what Charity can bid any man God Speed, in the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>Corah?</hi> or how can I affect his Society, that hates my Religion and my God? How can I bear it when I ſee my Saviour ſo manifeſtly <hi>Crucified afreſh;</hi> between the <hi>Heretick</hi> breaking the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the Church in point of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> by denying one or more of her Fundamental Articles; and the <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> in point of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> endeavouring to overthrow her Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? How can I endure another down-right <hi>Judas,</hi> to betray the whole Cauſe of Chriſtianity, with a complement of Religion, or a <hi>Kiſs</hi> of Zeal?</p>
            <p>Surely if we muſt <hi>withdraw</hi> from the <hi>Heretick</hi> (who if he keeps his error to himſelf,<note place="margin">Schiſm worſe than Hereſie.</note> may be no bodies foe but his own) then much more certainly from the <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> as the more <hi>Scandalous, Miſchievous</hi> and <hi>Impious</hi> of the two, as neceſſarily offending againſt <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> together;<note place="margin">And why.</note> becauſe the <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> cannot poſſibly keep his <hi>Schiſm</hi> to himſelf, that being publick in its own nature, as being a poſitive ſeparation from publick <hi>Worſhip,</hi> erecting Altar againſt Altar, and more than a bare negative ſuſpenſion of Communion, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence an <hi>affront</hi> to the Governours, and a <hi>ſcorn</hi> to the Government of the Church, by ſetting up a <hi>Conventicle</hi> prohibited by God and man, againſt a Church eſtabliſht by the Laws of both. The <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick</hi> is an <hi>actual divider</hi> in, and of the Church, and therefore worſe by odds than any other who is but paſſively <hi>divided,</hi> or cut off
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62834:14"/>
from her; as much worſe as to ſubvert the whole Legiſlative power, is worſe than any violation of a particular Law; or to make way for all the Hereſies and Immoralities in the world, is worſe than any one of thoſe can be.</p>
            <p>The Schiſmatick muſt needs be ſo much worſe than the Heretick, as a vicious <hi>practice</hi> is worſe than a falſe <hi>opinion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints. The Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick a Heretick too.</note> and as a Schiſmatick is for the moſt part <hi>ipſo facto</hi> an Heretick too; for I pray tell me does he not renounce the IXth Article of the Creed? does he not diſown (did I ſay) does he not deſpiſe and deteſt that great Fundamental and eſſential to all Chriſtian Religion, <hi>ſubmiſſion to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi> as well as our own? or tell me if this be not a moſt principal and fundamental doctrine.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, I beſeech you ſpeak out, Is it not a part of our Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to God himſelf? Is it not the apteſt of all others to keep the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the</hi> Spirit <hi>in the bond of Peace,</hi> and is it not therefore that we find no Doctrine in the Holy Scriptures, more earneſtly or more affiduouſly,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18.</note> more plainly or more expreſly preſcrib'd to us, than that of Uniform <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>all that are over us in authority,</hi> worſt as well as beſt? and therefore tell me again,</p>
            <p>Is it not both a moſt fooliſh and a moſt nefarious pretence, that the Religion or irreligion of our Governours can either widen or ſtraiten our divine obligation to ſtrict obedience? Tell me,</p>
            <p>Was there ever more incarnate devils than <hi>Nero</hi> or <hi>Tiberius,</hi> whom yet both Chriſt and St. <hi>Paul</hi> obeyed themſelves, and commanded others to obey?</p>
            <p>Tell me, Is not our obedience to Magiſtrates due to that Authority which has commanded us to pay it them? and therefore cannot be paid as due to the men as men, or to the good as good, but reduplicatively to the Magiſtrates as <hi>ſuch,</hi> let them be otherwiſe what they will, ſo they be not Uſurpers or command contrary to God, and then does not the very exception of thoſe caſes confirm the doctrine in all other? Tell me,</p>
            <p>Are we not when the commands of God and the King are inconſiſtent, then to give our whole active obedience to God, and to his Deputy our paſſive only? and is not the Kings command otherwiſe the command of God too, and is not the ſame Law <hi>mediately</hi> divine which is immediately humane, or are we more obliged by ſtrict precept to <hi>fear God</hi> than we are to <hi>honour the King;</hi> or more forbidden the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Idols than diſobedience to lawful Authority, or is any man able ſo much as in his conception to ſeparate the ſin of Schiſm from ſuch diſobedience, or ſuch diſobedience from rebellion againſt the Law of Chriſt, or a ſtate of damnation from either of them? Tell me,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:62834:14"/>Does not St. <hi>Jude</hi> put all theſe together in his deſcription of the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> the firſt and worſt Schiſmaticks,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jude</hi> 4, 8, 12, 16, 19.</note> Hereticks and Rebels in the Primitive Church, when he calls them <hi>Murmurers, Complainers, walking after</hi> their <hi>own luſts, ſeparating themſelves</hi> (from what I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 6.</note> if not from the Church eſtabliſht) <hi>having not</hi> (yet queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs pretending to have) <hi>the Spirit,</hi> whom he therefore parallels for their miſery as well as ſin, with thoſe that made a Schiſm as it were in Heaven, and ſeparated from the Church Triumphant, reſerved in <hi>everlaſting</hi> chains <hi>under</hi> darkneſs, unto the Judgment of the great day. Tell me,</p>
            <p>Are not thoſe who do not hold faſt the <hi>Profeſſion of the Faith,</hi> but <hi>forſake the aſſembling themſelves together</hi> (at ſtated times and places by juſt authority appointed) <hi>as the manner of ſome is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23, 25.</note> are not they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to <hi>ſin wilfully,</hi> and that therefore <hi>there remains nothing for ſuch, but a fearful looking for of judgment and fiery indignation?</hi> Do we not find the Holy Pen-men, thundring out the Terrors of the Lord againſt this ſingle ſin more than all the reſt? and why do we ſo, but becauſe this ſin gives the greateſt ſcandal to the enemies of Chriſt, and helps to juſtifie them in their higheſt prejudices to his Name and Goſpel? Do we not find the Schiſmaticks ſingled out from the whole herd of ſcandalous and notorious ſinners to be <hi>markt</hi> and <hi>avoided</hi> as the worſt of all, as moſt deſtitute of Chriſtian meekneſs, not <hi>conſenting</hi> to <hi>wholeſom words,</hi> but— <hi>proud, knowing nothing, doating about queſtions</hi> and <hi>ſtrifes</hi> of <hi>words,</hi> whereof <hi>cometh envy, ſtrife, &amp;c. preſumptuous, ſelf-will'd, deſpiſing Governments, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can any pride be more monſtrous than to be proud of knowledge, and yet know nothing? or can it be any other thing than ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted pride as this, that can make men of low Parts, and little Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of ordinary Education and mean Improvements, to ſeparate from this Great and Admired Church of <hi>England,</hi> from the ſolemn devotions of her Publick Liturgy, contriv'd by the Wiſdom, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Learning, embrac't by the Piety, eſtabliſht by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of ſuch a Nation? confirm'd by at leaſt 33 Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and as many Convocations, Signed and Sealed by the Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of ſo many Confeſſors and Martyrs, and ſince that Aſſerted againſt the wit and malice of all Opponents? Is not this ſuch an arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance of pride as no Rhetorick can expreſs, no Charity excuſe, no Humility not cenſure?</p>
            <p>And yet this is not all, we are not at the height yet, for do they not tell us plainly they could approve of many things even in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy it ſelf, if they were not impos'd by Law? Good God! that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62834:15"/>
ever men ſhould make the reaſon why they ought, the reaſon why they will not ſerve God decently and in order! that ever men ſhould chuſe to impoſe upon themſelves, that they might not be governed by others!</p>
            <p>Tell us once again (for 'tis hard to believe any thing againſt the reaſon of mankind) muſt Parliaments and Synods ſtoop and ſtrike fail to you? muſt all that is great or Sacred among us be expos'd and markt out for the objects of your contempt? will nothing pleaſe or content you, but the baſeſt and moſt unnatural ſubmiſſion of <hi>Antiquity</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> to your <hi>Wills?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luciferian pride.</note> This is ſo high a flight and to ſuch a pitch as none but the Son of the morning can ſurmount, it towrs to ſuch a leſſening of <hi>Credibility</hi> that without the help of a contrary to match it, it would hardly be believed by being (that for which ſome other things muſt be believed) inviſible. We could not ſo eaſily believe their <hi>Pride</hi> to be ſo great (as to make ſome men (in a woful ſence) little inferiour to ſome Angels) but that we feel their <hi>Charity</hi> to be as little.<note place="margin">Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs.</note> For do they think any thing but evil of us or towards us? They cannot ſee their own eyes nor the beams in them, but in the eye of a <hi>Conformiſt</hi> they can preſently ſpy the leaſt <hi>mote,</hi> yea and ſtare it into a <hi>mountain.</hi> They are ſo black jaundic't with malignity and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, that they can ſee nothing (no by no means nothing) but <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery</hi> or <hi>Paganiſm</hi> in all our ſervice of God. Tell us therefore, can you rationally deny that you eſteem us as bad as any <hi>Pagans?</hi> or can you excuſe your ſelves in that ſeparation if you judge not our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to be as abſolutely unlawful, as you judge your own to be abſolutely neceſſary to Salvation? Is not this your Charity? Gentlemen are you awake?<note place="margin">De <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Eccl.</note> do you hear St. <hi>Cyprian? macula iſta nec ſanguine abluitur,</hi> Martyrdome itſelf is not ſufficient to make amends for Schiſm. Are ye not frighted? How can the Father ſpeak truth if Schiſm be not exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of Chriſtian Charity? or if their Charity gives him the lye, I hope their Faith will be civiller to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and does not he plainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3.</note>
that whilſt we live in Schiſm we have no Charity, our Alms are no better than oſtentation, and the yielding our ſelves to be burnt, but a mad kind of Martyrdom, or rather but a fooliſh Sacrifice to humour and ſtomach; like that of <hi>Clement</hi> and <hi>Ravilliac</hi> who dyed Martyrs to the <hi>Papacy,</hi> or thoſe whom we read of to have been called <hi>(Martyres ſtultae Philoſophiae,)</hi> Martyrs of vain Philoſophy, or that which may ſerve for all the reſt, of our own <hi>Engliſh Regicides,</hi> to their <hi>Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm.</hi> They all dyed for the Deities they all adored.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Multiplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Sects.</note>As by this time we may juſtly doubt whether the abundance of Pride or want of Charity be greater in theſe men, ſo conſidering the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62834:15"/>
prolifick nature of all evil, and of this above all, we are like to doubt on ſtill, whether they do not paramount themſelves, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel their Eminencies before named in their exceeding plenty of <hi>diviſions.</hi> How many are the Sects that have been made by this devil <hi>Schiſm?</hi> were not all the calamities of <hi>England</hi> begun, continued, and (if ever they be compleated) muſt they not be finiſhed in thee?<note place="margin">The Black box.</note> Here's the <hi>Black box</hi> you talk on! a Box with a <hi>Vengeance! Pandora</hi>'s Box! How faſt 'tis ſeal'd up! hold, I think there's ſome Inſcription upon the Seals—<hi>Bul. P. Pi.</hi> 5.—<hi>Sol. Le. and Cov.</hi> Nay then I am reſolved I'le open it— It flyes like Bottle Ale, what are theſe papers that are tumbled out— Impeach. of <hi>Straff.</hi>— Impeach. of Arch B. <hi>L.</hi>— Inſtruct. for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbr. Tr.</hi>— Inſtructions for <hi>Conſults</hi>— Liſt of <hi>Kings Judges</hi>— Reaſons for Toleration—Conſiderations concerning <hi>Elections, &amp;c.</hi> Petitions againſt Proclamations. If theſe be the top, what's in the bottom? but I'le put them in again, for ought I know it may be as much as the Reputation of a Proteſtant is worth, but to look upon them; well, 'tis true I ſee (that by a little alluſion,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Cowley</hi>
               </note> I may gratifie my memory with a dear name)
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Schiſm;</hi> th'art a <hi>devil,</hi> if I may call thee <hi>one,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, by this <hi>Box,</hi> thy name is <hi>Legion.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
Didſt not thou ſet up an Heteroclite <hi>Aſſembly</hi> againſt a Regular <hi>Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> a vagrant <hi>Directory</hi> againſt a ſetled <hi>Liturgy?</hi> didſt not thou ſell the Lands firſt, and then the Head from the Crown? didſt not thou ſet up <hi>iniquity</hi> for <hi>Law,</hi> and ſtrength for an Hight Court of Juſtice? Was it not thou <hi>Schiſm!</hi> that foundedſt all Right in Dominion, and all Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion in Grace! was not <hi>Leviathan,</hi> or is not New <hi>Rome</hi> a ſpawn of thee thou curſed Dam of all the Blaſphemies and Hereſies of all times! Didſt not thou beget that mungrel <hi>Toleration,</hi> and <hi>expound</hi> Chriſtian Liberty into that <hi>ſenſe</hi> which we now all ſee, and (without the preventing mercy of God and vigilancy of our Governours) muſt feel too? and by the warmth of theſe didſt thou not hatch thoſe ugly mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters <hi>Ochlocracy</hi> and <hi>Anarchy,</hi> and haſt thou not been brooding of theſe ever ſince the Reſtauration of <hi>England</hi> to it ſelf, or the King to <hi>England?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which laſt reſpect as thou art every where black and blue by thy envious and malignant nature, thou art yet uglier and more odious here by thy moſt ſuperlative ingratitude. Who can be that Viperous gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of more proper name than they that undermine and conſpire againſt thoſe Laws and Legiſlators, by and under which they have and hold the greateſt earthly enjoyments, and this whilſt themſelves (or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62834:16"/>
the chiefeſt among them) confeſs us <hi>Proteſtants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Indifferent things no cauſe for ſeparation.</note> and can ſhew no greater or other cauſe for their Animoſities, than our injoyning ſome indifferent things uncommanded in the Scripture, which is ſuch a cauſe as muſt equally engage them againſt all the Reformed Churches in <hi>Europe,</hi> in which there muſt be ſome indifferent things, and ſo againſt themſelves too.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The name of Jeſus adorable.</note>The Bowing at the Name of <hi>Jeſus</hi> is none of thoſe things, and the offence they take therefore is not given: for admitting <hi>what they object,</hi> that the practice is neither warranted nor intended by the Apoſtle in that common Text, yet certainly thoſe mighty peculiar <hi>Emphaſes</hi> which we find put by the Spirit of Truth upon that <hi>all-adored</hi> and <hi>ſalvifick</hi> name, muſt needs enforce it. Have the Angels in their more exalted nature, have they knees for this <hi>hyperhypſiſtous Immanuel,</hi> and can the Chriſtian man have none for the ſame ſuperexcelling and moſt exalted <hi>Jeſus?</hi> do they bow <hi>inquiſitively,</hi> ſhall the mountains and rocks bow <hi>litterally,</hi> and can I not bow <hi>Religiouſly?</hi> muſt my underſtanding bow (or break) to the <hi>Faith</hi> of the incarnation, and can my body (in this ſtate of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi>) not bow at the Name, or (which is all one) at the mention or memory of <hi>God incarnate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Verſus, &amp;c. Typical.</note>And for the like reaſon, though bowing towards the <hi>Temple (Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem)</hi> were Typical then, yet bowing in the Temple or houſe of Prayer even by the practice of the Antitype it ſelf muſt be pious ſtill; and that place as ſeparated and conſecrated by Chriſt, ſo hallowed and eſteemed by us.<note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> The Philoſopher can tell us that a <hi>lye</hi> is <hi>malum in ſe,</hi> a ſin againſt the Law of our <hi>Nature,</hi> therefore to make a <hi>lye (quod efficit tale)</hi> muſt be ſo and more; and to violence or captivate a profitable truth can be little leſs; the good which I do againſt my mind is ſo far hypocriſie, as the evil which I ſo do is infirmity; and there is <hi>crimen falſi</hi> in both; when I bow my body to the perſon I had rather ſtab, or kiſs the hand that I wiſh cut off, does not my ſoul make my body <hi>lye?</hi> ſo when my ſoul bows in Adoration of God, can it ſo exclude the body in this ſtate of conjunction, as either to deny the right or interdict the uſe of its aſſiſtance? would not ſuch excluſion be an injurious reſtraint and oppreſſion of that truth which I am always bound to own and aſſert by a <hi>reaſonable ſervice of God,</hi> with my <hi>whole man,</hi> my ſoul and body to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether? We grant 'tis the Loyalty of the ſoul that makes a true Chriſtian ſubject, yet we know this never is or can be unattended by the hand and knee too.<note place="margin">Voluptas animae anima voluptatis.</note> We grant that as the pleaſure of the Soul is the ſoul of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſo the worſhip of the Soul or Spirit is the ſoul of worſhip, but then this ſoul is in the body ſtill and acts not but ecſtatically without it, and it acts as diſtinctly, as groſly bodily in any determinate poſition of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62834:16"/>
the hand or eye, as in the flex on of the back or knee, all are alike bodily worſhip, and equally lyable to exception, though their fortune has not been alike: if there be any difference in the notoriety of the geſtures, then we ſay, the more viſible, (if decent and Analogous) the more <hi>honorary;</hi> we think it impoſſible for any ſoul ſeriouſly militant, to think it adviſeable to throw away his arms, or give them up to his enemy, to give that bow or worſhip to any creature, which upon the oath and fidelity of a ſouldier he muſt give to, and only to his Creator; he muſt bow as <hi>ſpiritually</hi> and <hi>litterally</hi> too as he muſt not bow; yea he muſt bow as naturally and neceſſarily (whilſt he is in the body) as he muſt not; he cannot enter the houſe, or begin the work of Prayer, without bowing forth his <hi>Domine non ſum dignus,</hi> nor make any ſolemn re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious addreſs without the Soul of a Chriſtian, and the body of a man together; the negative precept both directs and confirms the poſitive duty, and by being commanded <hi>not</hi> we are inſtructed <hi>how</hi> to bow; look what ſhare he knows his body muſt have in the violation, he gives it the ſame in the performance of his duty, and is ſo well perſwaded of the reaſonableneſs of this ſervice, that, without doing open violence to the expreſs command by hacking out a piece (as ſome of our Schiſmaticks acquaintance have cut off the whole) and reſtively ſtopping at <hi>(thou ſhalt not bow)</hi> he cannot conceive the leaſt colourable objection againſt this, or in favour of the contrary practice, unleſs either it ſhould be ſaid here (as we have heard before) that it muſt not be done becauſe commanded, which God forbid; or that it could be thought argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative or not <hi>Sarcaſtical;</hi> which I remember to have ſeen ſomewhere produced by a perſon of Honour as the only Text, that can piece up the rent of that mutilate Communion in the Church of <hi>Rome, viz.— Father, if it be poſſible let this cup paſs from me, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be the pinch is not ſo much here, and they are more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended as <hi>Engliſh</hi> men than as Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Where the pinch lyes.</note> as abridged of thoſe privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges which their intereſt in <hi>Magna Charta</hi> claims for them, that they are not admitted to places of truſt and office, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Truly we might wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly endure the envy of this objection upon condition it were but as true in <hi>Theſi</hi> as it would be abſurd in <hi>Hypotheſi.</hi> For, beſides that we know by ſad and memorable experience, were Schiſmaticks Legiſlators, they would certainly inforce ſuch a <hi>Conformity,</hi> as they will now nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comply with themſelves, nor forgive in others, they have made themſelves even by their own Principles incapable of being what they complain they are not; for if indifferent things are not properly the matter of humane Laws, as <hi>humane</hi> is contradiſtinct to <hi>divine,</hi> there's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the world beſides that can be ſo, becauſe all neceſſary things
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62834:17"/>
are already ſufficiently commanded, and all unlawful things as evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently forbidden in the Word of God, in which reſpect they are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether divine and in no wiſe humane Laws; ſo that there could be but one Law (preciſely humane) which the Schiſmatick Legiſlator could poſſibly enact,<note place="margin">The Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maticks Law.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>every Chriſtian ſhould be a law unto himſelf,</hi> or the ſame in other words, that every mans reaſon ſhould be his guide, and every mans <hi>will</hi> ſhould be his <hi>Law,</hi> and conſequently that all ſhould be rulers as much as any.</p>
            <p>May we not now appeal unto themſelves whether they be not of all Recuſants the moſt unexcuſable, more than thoſe that are <hi>toſſed about with every wind of falſe doctrine,</hi> when not our Doctrines (true or falſe) but our bare <hi>Surplices</hi> can skare them, or our <hi>Organs</hi> blow them out of the Church? whether it had not been better for them never to have been the members of Chriſt, than being ſuch to out <hi>themſelves</hi> off from his <hi>Body which is the Church?</hi> whether it were not fitter, ſeeing common ſafety cannot always ſubſiſt without publick peace, nor publick peace without compliance on one ſide or other, whether I ſay it were not fitter, that the Inferiours, the fewer and the more igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, ſhould yield, to the Superiours, the many and the more learned? and this ſo much the rather, if it be well conſidered that however Chriſtians ought to <hi>ſerve one another in love,</hi> yet obedience to inferiours is grievous and not without ſome excuſe for being ſo; whereas that of Superiours (as of Chriſt (who according to his humane nature was a ſubject) to <hi>Caeſar</hi>) is a moſt noble, natural and neceſſary duty, as that which ſupports the whole Fabrick of the Church and of all the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms upon earth, and in Heaven too, that which is ſo equally eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to Policy and Religion, that 'tis plainly impoſſible either for <hi>Saints</hi> to be <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> or <hi>Rebels,</hi> or for ſuch to be Saints without making our Faith, our Scriptures, our Religion vain, without a down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right welcome to <hi>Anarchy,</hi> and farewel to all Society.</p>
            <p>The contempt of Authority linked with an obſtinate contumacious and ſeditious humour, is ſo very a monſter, that it makes an error of judgment, which might otherwiſe have been <hi>venial</hi> in it ſelf, a diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical and damning quality. So that if <hi>Schiſm</hi> were no ſuch ſin as it is, yet it were worth the parting with, for the purchaſe of publick peace, of which rightly improved, piety and proſperity, ſtrength and ſafety, are the genuine and precious fruits. It was for <hi>this</hi> that our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf complyed in ſome things, both with <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> that he might gain both. It was for <hi>this</hi> that we find the like complyances of St. <hi>Paul</hi> (of whom we ſhould all be followers as he was of Chriſt) yielding to circumciſe <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15.28, 29.</note> and refuſing again to circumciſe <hi>Titus.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:62834:17"/>
To gain the <hi>Jews</hi> he denyed himſelf the uſe of his Chriſtian liberty, and reſum'd it again to gain the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> It was for peace and to unite diſſenters, that the Apoſtles made that conciliar eſtabliſhment of things indifferent by a Law whereby they induced a neceſſity <hi>à parte poſt</hi> upon things indifferent <hi>à parte antè.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this Apoſtolical practice as it plainly informs our judgments in the true ſubject matter of humane Laws, and whereabout they are <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly</hi> converſant, and as plainly directs our practice of obedience in ſuch caſes, ſo will it never be made to ſerve their purpoſes, who, by binding the whole force and weight of it upon their Governours ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſo as they themſelves may not touch it ſo much as with one of their own fingers, would make it a ground of exception from the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral rule of ſubmiſſion, and a warrant to diſpute at leaſt, and (as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly follows) to deny at <hi>laſt</hi> that obedience which they pretend according to this practice ſhould not have been commanded; as if the condeſcenſion and indulgence of Governours were not to the ignorance or frowardneſs, to the <hi>intellectual</hi> or <hi>moral</hi> infirmities of diſſenters; as if the <hi>Jews</hi> had not been culpable in their tenaciouſneſs of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> when St. <hi>Paul</hi> purpoſely ſtoopt to them and approved its obſervance by his own practice; as if the bowels and forbearings of any injur'd and incens'd Parent did not make it more the childs duty to love and honour him, and ſhould not make it more his ſhame and grief to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe him, more his ſin and guilt to diſobey him; as if not preſently to take the forfeiture, were reaſonably to avoid the debt, or cancel the debtors obligation; or as if it were equally of duty, as it is of power in the Prince to ſuſpend the execution of a known Law, for ſome weighty reaſons of State, and upon the proſpect of publick benefit, and to tolerate a practice againſt Law and without hope of any common good, and not without juſt apprehenſions of the greateſt experience of the contrary, and therefore againſt all the reaſon in the world, but that of his own courteſie and meer pity.</p>
            <p>'Tis true indeed when <hi>Kings</hi> are <hi>ſaid to be Gods,</hi> we beſt underſtand how they are ſuch, when they are ſaid alſo to be <hi>nurſing Fathers,</hi> and therefore without fear either of contradiction to ſenſe, or of courtſhip againſt reaſon, we can ſay they are <hi>humane Gods,</hi> their <hi>deity</hi> beſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted by their <hi>humanity,</hi> and both by a joynt ſupremacy of <hi>power</hi> and <hi>goodneſs,</hi> and we cannot chuſe but wonder at the Anti-ſupremacy of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> that our ready obedience ſhould not confeſs the one as irreſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as our rebellions have prov'd the other.</p>
            <p>'Tis as true, that there is no ſuch <hi>mirrour</hi> ſo clear and true to look in, no ſuch optick or perſpicil to ſee with, as is the <hi>Cryſtal</hi> of the Word
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62834:18"/>
of <hi>God;</hi> a glaſs of ſuch virtue that it not only moſt perfectly diſcovers the <hi>object</hi> but alſo diſpoſes the <hi>medium,</hi> and directs the <hi>faculty;</hi> a glaſs that will never ſuffer us to behold any thing with or through prejudice or baſe intereſt, or without Chriſtian charity and meekneſs; a glaſs that never ſhews us the ſpots of others but by <hi>reflexion</hi> upon our own; in this glaſs we can neither behold the virtues or vices of our fellow-ſubjects with <hi>envy,</hi> or without <hi>pity,</hi> nor the blemiſhes or beauties of our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, without a <hi>reverence</hi> becoming both; a reverence I ſay as being a mixt affection of fear and love, by which I <hi>fear</hi> the power whilſt I love not the fault of the perſon, and love the perſon whilſt I fear the evil, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſin or puniſhment, of the fault. In this glaſs we ſee what we muſt piouſly bewail, yet may not proudly cenſure in our <hi>Superiors;</hi> what we muſt reprove with <hi>caution</hi> and without arrogance in our <hi>equals;</hi> and what we muſt judge and condemn impartially, poſitively, abſolutely and irreſpectively (to any though more ſcandalous ſins of others) in our ſelves; St. <hi>Paul</hi> was the greateſt of ſinners, with the greateſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Salvation; and the Publican was a ſinner with more comfort, than the <hi>Phariſee</hi> was not a <hi>Publican.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this glaſs the moſt abſolute Soveraign Prince may beſt ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the fulleſt proportion; he ſees by and for whom he <hi>reigns abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely,</hi> and without whom he reigns not <hi>independently;</hi> he ſees that his Government is <hi>arbitrary</hi> as that is <hi>ſupream</hi> and unqueſtionable by man, but not as any way unaccountable, but as every way moſt ſtrictly and moſt eſpecially <hi>accountable</hi> to God, for he ſees him that is properly and ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally King of Kings, under whoſe moſt ſupreme and comprehenſive Title, and by vertue of whom he ſees himſelf conſtituted and authorized, and accordingly to which he is to be directed, limited and ſubordinate, and therefore by no means to intrench upon the Prerogatives Royal of his Lord Paramount, and therefore not to govern by his own <hi>Will,</hi> which is Gods peculiar, a <hi>rule</hi> to himſelf, and a <hi>Law</hi> to the Sons of men, the root and ſource of all Government, which ſo ſpreads and runs it ſelf through the whole nature of man, that it makes Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not more <hi>divine</hi> in it ſelf than <hi>connatural</hi> to us, and as effective of our well-beings in Societies as of our ſocial and conjugal propenſions, and therefore as old as <hi>Paternity</hi> it ſelf, or the Firſt of the Firſt-born, making every man naturally ſociable,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Supremum, medium, ultimum.</note> and actually diſpoſed and tending to Societies, which therefore cannot poſſibly conſiſt without Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor <hi>that</hi> without order, nor <hi>this</hi> without degrees of ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and therefore alſo becauſe the foundations of Government are thus laid in our very natures, there is nothing that can lay nearer to theſe foundations, or be as we ſay, more fundamental or eſſential to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62834:18"/>
Government than our obedience to the Laws of men, and their confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Laws of God; he plainly ſees and contemplates the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty of God, that <hi>all power belongeth unto him, that dominion and fear are with him, both in heaven and in earth, and for ever</hi> in both, and thereby ſupples and tempers his Prerogatives againſt all immoderate aſſumings to himſelf, or encroachments upon his people; he can never meaſure himſelf by himſelf, whilſt he compares himſelf with his God; inſtead of that turgid Interrogation— <hi>Is not this great Babel,</hi> which I have built, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he makes this of moſt humble admiration— <hi>Lord! what is man! what ſhall I render</hi> to thy mercy, or anſwer to thy juſtice! how ſhall I uſurp thy right or pervert thy favour! how ſhall I diſcharge my truſt and give up my account with joy! In this contemplation the Prince mounts indeed, but 'tis to a leſſening of himſelf, and magnifying of his God.</p>
            <p>And as the Prince ſo the ſubject is ſufficiently inſtructed in the nature of his obedience, and knows it to be the ſame which he performs to God for his own ſake, and to man for Gods ſake, and therefore dares not but diſtinguiſh thus, as he dares not otherwiſe between the <hi>perſon</hi> and <hi>office</hi> of the Governour, that he pays not his obedience to the man as man (gentle or <hi>froward</hi>) but to the man as Magiſtrate and only ſo.</p>
            <p>Thus this Theam of Gods univerſal, abſolute and everlaſting power, will prove a ſufficient Amulet againſt all the charms of tyranny of all ſorts, as well that of <hi>injuſtice</hi> or <hi>oppreſſion</hi> in the Governour, as that (the more miſchievous and leſs tolerable of the two) that of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> in the Subjects, who in Conſcience of this truth, of their own accords cannot but recognize their <hi>Prince,</hi> as Gods imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate <hi>Vice-gerent,</hi> and higheſt <hi>Commiſſioner</hi> amongſt men, and that therefore no man or men in the moſt collective ſence (for that nothing leſs can by any means be inferr'd from the moſt important negative in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogation <hi>who?) can ſay unto him what doſt thou?</hi> he ſees him <hi>ſingulia &amp; omnibus major,</hi> but neither ſeeks nor hopes nor deſires to find him <hi>univerſis minor.</hi> He improves the Wiſe mans counſel of <hi>not curſing</hi> the King, no not in a thought, into not ſo much as thinking diſloyally; ſo far is he from writing rebelliouſly— <hi>To your Tents O Iſrael, &amp;c.</hi> or from ſpeaking and threatning ſeditiouſly, that— <hi>deliverance ſhall come another way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He dares not pretend a kindneſs for the <hi>perſon,</hi> which he intends againſt the <hi>Government</hi> of his Prince, or by a moſt abominable and fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitious <hi>ſuperfaetation</hi> hatch one plot under the heat of zeal againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>He is willing as much as in him lyes to <hi>have peace with all men,</hi> and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:62834:19"/>
to look gently upon the errors of others, as rather to be of ignorance, and only conſequentially or indirectly ſuch; whilſt yet he obſerves many ſorts of men <hi>explicitly</hi> and profeſſedly renouncing thoſe erroneous opinions, which notwithſtanding they do <hi>virtually</hi> abet, and <hi>implicitly</hi> defend under the patronage of ſome other they think leſs obvious or leſs obnoxious principles, and whilſt they declaim <hi>pathetically</hi> againſt the Treaſon acted upon the Firſt, and contriv'd againſt the Second <hi>Charles,</hi> and in the ſame heat of breath againſt thoſe Jeſuitical doctrines of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicating, Murdering or Depoſing Kings, are content in the mean time to ſend thoſe Kings to the people for their power, and as the peoples Stewards to give up their accounts of Government to them alſo; ſo the Papiſt (that <hi>incorrigible</hi> becauſe <hi>infallible</hi> Schiſmatick) bears himſelf high upon the tiptoes and magiſtery of ſence and reaſon, whilſt by his moſt beloved Tranſubſtantiation he affronts both; ſo the Atheiſt whilſt he cannot deny a Firſt and eternal cauſe, will not yet ſo much as conceive the more evident exiſtence of a Spirit; if theſe errors be no worſe deſcended than from ignorance or inadvertency, he hopes the bare naming of them ſufficient for their conviction, but if mixt with obſtinacy or intereſt of a <hi>Party,</hi> he quits them as impregnable againſt all the batteries of <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Religion;</hi> however even againſt theſe he dares not magnifie himſelf, but deſires rather to be humbled unto duſt for them, and under the deepeſt ſenſe of his own frailty, the guilt and danger of ſin, and the memory of that ſignal wrath which has been ſo expreſly <hi>revealed from Heaven againſt</hi> us <hi>the children of diſobedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this glaſs the Prince beſt ſees and feels too how handſomly or eaſily his Crown ſits, if it be irradiated with the <hi>GLORIES</hi> of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Sincerity,</hi> if illuſtrated with the greater and more luminous reſplendencies of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> (what a bald-crown'd head were that, that could not pardon?) and with the leſſer twinkling eyes, yet truly orient and genuine ſparks of <hi>Temperance</hi> and <hi>Affability;</hi> and with theſe bigger and leſſer Luminaries, the Prince in peace and proſperity, in ſafety and joy, in reputation and honour, ſhines directly upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and more <hi>obliquely</hi> but not leſs <hi>beneficially</hi> on all his Subjects; he <hi>ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters iniquity</hi> and conciliates Majeſty with theſe eyes.</p>
            <p>Yet as the <hi>natural</hi> eye-ſight is weakned if fixt over long, or too intently upon the ſame object; ſo theſe <hi>Political</hi> eyes of <hi>Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> by looking too hard and too <hi>wiſsly,</hi> or too long and too <hi>indulgently,</hi> may be dazled into rigorous <hi>ſeverity</hi> or cruel <hi>pity;</hi> in which caſes if it could be duty to <hi>put</hi> the queſtion, there might be reaſon enough to <hi>make</hi> it, whether the Prince had not better borrow other mens eyes, than thus uſe his own, or were not more inexcuſable than if he had never
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62834:19"/>
lookt in this glaſs, or whether the vicinity of ſome gliſtering metals may not obſcure or diſadvantage the brightneſs of the pureſt gold, or that it would not be a diſparagement to the Royal vertue of <hi>Clemency,</hi> if ſuch a miſtaken pity ſhould be ſtill miſ-plac't, and find ſuch a noble un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſeeming ſhelter in the courteſie of the Princes nature, where it not only gets <hi>protection</hi> from the purſuit of obloquy, where Chriſtian loyalty governs the very tongue; but works it ſelf into <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> too, and makes the <hi>pitying,</hi> in the beſt Tranſlation the moſt <hi>pityed,</hi> and in the vulgar, the moſt <hi>pitiful</hi> Prince, or that it would not be an infelicity, if it were not a fault, and if it did not ſully his Robes, would not probably dusk the luſtre of his Name, which the Prince cannot but diſcern in this glaſs, where he ſees plainly that the mercies of the wicked are cruel, and that the indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences of the good may be ſo too; for Charity being of an active diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and walking much abroad would be very often affronted, either ſlighted by the ingratitude of ſome, or juſtled, or perhaps aſſaulted by the perverſeneſs of others, or betrayed by her own goodneſs, if ſhe were not ſometimes attended and guarded by ſeverity.</p>
            <p>Without this, how eaſily might ſhe be ſtroakt and ſoftned into a cruel and dangerous impunity, by indulging (not the weaklings or fearful ones, but) the ſtout and ſtubborn, the obſtinate and malitious, the deſigning and incorrigible offenders, ſuch as corrupt themſelves with goodneſs, and turn the <hi>flat</hi> of indulgence into the <hi>edge</hi> of preſumption, and at the next turn into the <hi>point</hi> of direct enmity.</p>
            <p>The Prince ſees all this, and more than this, when he conſiders his <hi>Purple</hi> of ſo pure a dye, that the ſmalleſt ſoil will ſpot it, and the leaſt ſpot will diſcolour it; his Crown of ſo fine a <hi>make,</hi> ſo eminent a <hi>ſite,</hi> ſuch a tranſparent <hi>ſplendour,</hi> that even a <hi>mote</hi> of imperfection may be ſeen in it, much more would any <hi>cloud</hi> be notorious, which beſides what it gathered of its own from any noxious morbifick <hi>exhalations,</hi> would not fail of ſome malevolent <hi>aſpects</hi> to thicken it into the <hi>darkneſs</hi> and then ſpread it into the <hi>inauſpiciouſneſs</hi> of ſome ſtrange and prodigious <hi>Eclipſe,</hi> Prognoſticated by the conjunction, cauſed by the <hi>inter-op-poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>harangued</hi> into the <hi>defection</hi> of ſome great bodies. So much need and uſe has the Prince of this true glaſs to ſee himſelf, when ſo many falſe ones are made by others to ſee him with.</p>
            <p>Hitherto we have beheld the Prince viewing himſelf impartially, and looking graciouſly upon all his Subjects that are or ſhould be ſuch, and they again beholding their Prince in the ſame glaſs but not with the ſame eyes, ſome with an eye of <hi>reverence,</hi> or religious fear and love, ſome with an eye of <hi>jealouſie</hi> or fear deſigned for hate, as that for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and theſe becauſe they look not, like thoſe, <hi>directly</hi> from God
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62834:20"/>
to the command and from that to the duty, but <hi>aſquint</hi> or acroſs, from God <hi>obliquely</hi> or in pretence, but then moſt <hi>directly</hi> to the Party or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and from that croſs again upon the preſcribed duty; we cannot ſee them ſufficiently (who look ſo many ſeveral ways) at one view.</p>
            <p>Sometimes they amuſe us with cloſe and warm inſinuations of <hi>fears</hi> and <hi>jealouſies,</hi> and ſo ſcatter the ſeeds of diſcontent; thus by a pretended <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi> they make way for <hi>Anarchy,</hi> and by fictitious for real Popery, the Devil and ſhame together teaching them to colour <hi>Schiſm</hi> with Zeal, and to ſute their <hi>mediums</hi> of ſuggeſtions or accuſations with their <hi>ends</hi> of ruin and deſtruction. Sometimes (like Tumblers) they ſee beſt with one of their eyes, their left eye ſharp-ſighted enough, when their right eye is <hi>full of darkneſs;</hi> thus they obtrude upon us <hi>worldly wiſdom,</hi> which we ſee they have, for <hi>divine light</hi> which we know they have not. Thus they teach humor and <hi>confidence</hi> inſtead of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and act accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly through thick and thin, they'l boggle or ſtop at nothing when the devil rides them, <hi>i. e.</hi> as they love to miſtake it, when <hi>conſcience overacts</hi> them, then, ſhew them if you can thoſe impieties which they dare not act to make them ſure of their Election: In this carier they have done ſuch feats in our memory, ſo black and execrable, exploits ſo exactly Theatrical and infernal, that their own Father might learn to act after them; that charity it ſelf could do them no greater kindneſs, than to make them (if not <hi>penitently innocent</hi>) leſs <hi>nocent unavoidably,</hi> that ſo if they will not <hi>chuſe</hi> the honour or comfort, they might be mercifully <hi>compelled</hi> to enjoy the common benefits of obedience, ſo that however they will periſh by other ſins, they might not be able to damn themſelves by Rebellion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Popiſh Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</note>Some of them that have traded longer than the reſt and ſet up for whole-ſale, have ingroſt that moſt comprehenſive falſhood <hi>Infallibility,</hi> as the ſureſt ſtaple error to advance trade, and help off the reſt; 'tis odds but ſome of them heretofore were near choaking (for I think they eat bones and all) with their <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and this <hi>infallible cruſt</hi> was firſt prepared to cure them, and ever ſince adminiſtred to all for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the like danger; ſurely a moſt ſoveraign remedy! for by keeping the gullet thus at ſtretch, and the ſwallow wide enough open, it makes all ſafe.<note place="margin">Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the IV. in Counc. of <hi>Trent.</hi>
               </note> Since that they have been able to take down XII Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles more than ever the Apoſtles took up, into their Creed preſcribed by one of their infallible Doctors, and prepared by his truſty Trojans, his Apothecaries of <hi>Trent,</hi> they can ſwallow the whole 24 together, at one gulp without check or chewing; and can we think now they ſhould ſtick or ſtrain at a <hi>Bolus</hi> of one man, the man <hi>Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> they are foully wrong'd if they be not now endeavouring to do as much by St. <hi>George</hi> for <hi>England</hi> and his <hi>horſe</hi> too.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:62834:20"/>Some of them look croſs upon the whole Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Antinomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> as if our free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from the rigour of that were our exemption from the bond of all humane Laws, and licentiouſneſs of life were the true Chriſtian liberty, or as if that liberty were not a manumiſſion from the <hi>bondage</hi> and <hi>domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> of ſin and Satan, but from the <hi>yoke</hi> of Chriſt and the precepts of Chriſtianity, and from the not only <hi>Poſitive</hi> but <hi>Moral</hi> Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which we know is the Law of Nature and of Chriſt too; as if they were free to regulate the Laws by their own humours, and not theſe by thoſe, as if no errours of judgment, no not blaſpheming or denying God were to be <hi>corrected</hi> or <hi>reſtrained</hi> by Laws; as if it were not the ſin but the duty of the Magiſtrate when he <hi>beareth</hi> the <hi>ſword</hi> in <hi>vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some look upward with ſuch bold and fixed ſtaring upon the decrees of God as ſuch abſolute irreſpective and irreverſible things,<note place="margin">Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narians.</note> as do eternally determine both the <hi>end</hi> and the <hi>means,</hi> and <hi>neceſſitate</hi> both our <hi>ſins</hi> and our <hi>puniſhments,</hi> and therefore warrant us to live, as we were born, without care; for that our <hi>vices</hi> cannot hurt us if <hi>Elect,</hi> nor our <hi>vertues</hi> help us if <hi>Reprobate;</hi> for that either we cannot repent if we would, or that we muſt repent do what we can; that whatever comes to paſs was antecedently unavoidable, and we thereby fully diſcharged of any farther care or ſolicitude, concerning our actions or our ends, and may therefore, as our complexions diſpoſe us, go <hi>merrily</hi> or <hi>deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly</hi> to hell, but go however; whereas would they but conſider them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as bound in duty, not to think or ſpeak any thing unworthy of God, or any thing which they would be aſhamed ſhould be thought or ſpoken of themſelves, they could not but conceive and acknowledge, that God's promiſes and threats are <hi>general</hi> and <hi>conditional;</hi> that his <hi>decrees</hi> are juſt, and ſo <hi>incluſive</hi> of his dealing with all men according to their deeds, and <hi>excluſive</hi> of any <hi>reſpect of perſons,</hi> and therefore that juſtification doth not precede Repentance, nor repentance avail without amendment, that ſin is not forgiven before committed, or before repented, and that therefore repentance muſt be in time, and juſtification which follows it (as well as pardon) muſt be ſo too.</p>
            <p>Some <hi>look</hi> down ſo brutiſhly upon one extreme,<note place="margin">The Sepa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ratiſt and Debaucher or Anti-hypocrite</note> that they never can advert to the other, one is ſo wholly intent upon his <hi>jealouſies</hi> of <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> that he never ſees or fears <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>diſobedience,</hi> whilſt another in avoidance of this <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> ruſhes into a worſe extream of <hi>Debauchery,</hi> and is ſo reſolv'd an <hi>anti-hypocrite,</hi> that he will not endure ſo much as a <hi>form</hi> of <hi>godlineſs,</hi> but rather than ſeem religious will <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim his ſin as Sodom;</hi> rather than <hi>hypocritically</hi> abſtain from the <hi>appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of <hi>evil,</hi> and not from the <hi>evil</hi> it ſelf, as the other doth, he will abſtain <hi>impudently</hi> both from <hi>good</hi> and from its <hi>appearance;</hi> and though a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62834:21"/>
of Chriſtianity, will vye with the <hi>effronteries</hi> of the moſt ſhameleſs <hi>Heathens,</hi> in diſcloſing thoſe <hi>pudendous</hi> enormities which he hath done, and that he may not be out-done, in boaſting of more than he ever had the appetite, or (if that yet) poſſibly the ſtrength to perpetrate, thus he hates hypocriſie <hi>worſe</hi> than the other loves it, and by glorying in his impiety, not only <hi>diſpleaſeth,</hi> but as the more horrid Devil of the two, even <hi>deſpiſeth</hi> God.</p>
            <p>It would be endleſs to remark upon the numberleſs diviſions and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſions of Sectaries, yet all equally pretending to be, and (how ill ſoever or awry they look) to be lookt upon by us as our reformers, all equally <hi>diſſenters</hi> from, <hi>Reformers</hi> without, and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> againſt autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, all equally <hi>admirers</hi> of themſelves and <hi>deſpiſers</hi> of their Superiors. Now what a monſter think we were that Church like to be, whoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or reformation were thus effected, that were to be lickt into ſhape and feature by the poyſonous ſlavering tongues of all theſe! or what can we imagine would look liker the abomination of deſolation!</p>
            <p>All this while the Holy, Humble, Sincere-hearted man, that <hi>trembles at the word of God, and is afraid of his judgments,</hi> or in other words, the truly Loyal and Chriſtian ſubject, he looks directly with eaſe and pleaſure into the <hi>perfect Law of liberty,</hi> his <hi>magna charta</hi> indeed, where he finds his priviledge in his duty, and his <hi>liberty</hi> in his <hi>obedience;</hi> his <hi>fear</hi> is not taught <hi>him by the Traditions</hi> or practices, the policies or proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of men. He has learnt <hi>whom to fear,</hi> and for whom; the Lord for his own ſake, and the King for the Lord's ſake; both or neither. He meaſures his whole Religion by his adequate obedience to God and man; and his whole obedience by the Law of God, whether bidding him <hi>(ſemper)</hi> obey <hi>his</hi> Rulers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or forbidding him <hi>(ad ſemper)</hi> to worſhip Idols, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Both are alike his duty, alike conducible to his Salvation, alike (when tranſgreſt) threatned with Damnation, and therefore reckons that he <hi>muſt needs be ſubject, not only for</hi> fear of <hi>wrath</hi> or hope of profit, for fear of hell or hope of Heaven, but <hi>for Conſcience</hi> towards God and our ſelves; for that this precept of obedience is not only <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentially</hi> good as every poſitive Law is, but <hi>ſimply good,</hi> and ſo <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedently</hi> obliging as a part of the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> without any rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the written Law, which here ſerves only to make diſobedience more unexcuſable, and under a greater condemnation. Wherefore he ſtill reckons on, that no <hi>form of godlineſs</hi> can be more than ſo without common honeſty, no common honeſty without giving all their dues, nothing more due than what the ſubject owes to the Soveraign; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he concludes that diſhoneſty, as ſuch, is ungodlineſs and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as ſcandalous as drunkenneſs or adultery. Thus the good ſubject
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:62834:21"/>
has review'd himſelf, but cannot go from the glaſs without a dutious filial reflection upon his Prince; let us attend him in this poſture alſo, and mark what he reports from his own eyes.</p>
            <p>He tells us he once ſaw in this glaſs, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that exemplar and ornament of Royalty, the Firſt <hi>CHARLES</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> ſo like as only not equal to his Prince and Saviour; in his Solitudes a Prophet, in his Sufferings both King and Prieſt, or according to that new name receiv'd at his ſecond Baptiſm, the <hi>ROYAL MARTYR:</hi> in the circumſtances of his Apprehenſion, and Arraignment, in the matter of his Charge and Defence, the manner of his Death and Burial, in the glorious Reſurrection of his Name and Memory, (a name embalm'd with ſpices of its own) in his living to do good and dying to do more, yea in dying expreſly to ſave his Peoples Liberties and Properties, he hath ſo reviv'd the hiſtory of the Croſs, that he can ſee Chriſt in this his Principal member Crucified again, He can point to the Council, to the Souldiers, to the <hi>Judas,</hi> to the <hi>Pilate,</hi> to the <hi>Golgotha, &amp;c.</hi> He bids us remember we had, Alas that we had! ſuch a Prince; of Piety to that degree as was alone ſufficient to add the <hi>exceſs</hi> to our iniquity, and <hi>faſcination</hi> to the Rebellion of his people; and were not <hi>Oblivion</hi> enacted into duty, he could never forget— <hi>Exit Tyrannus Regum ultimus,</hi> So dy'd that worſt of Tyrants and laſt of Kings, that ingrain as engraven Inſcription of our Antiplaſtical <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector— Exeo Martyr Populi,</hi> Behold I dye the Martyr of the People, that innocent and Heroick expiration of the <hi>Royal Sufferer.</hi> However he'l be ſure to remember to pray that— <hi>Ne ſit Martyr in populum,</hi> his bloud might not be a witneſs againſt theſe Nations, might not be upon us and upon our children, may at laſt be the merciful ſentence of the ſupreme <hi>Avenger. Amen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amen.</note>
            </p>
            <p>He now ſees in the ſame glaſs, by a providence as full of mercy as wonder, another <hi>CHARLES,</hi> a <hi>Second</hi> from the <hi>Firſt,</hi> there's a ſpecialty of <hi>mercy;</hi> and a <hi>Second</hi> to that <hi>Firſt,</hi> there's the wonder. Such a <hi>Second</hi> to ſuch a <hi>Firſt</hi> muſt needs demonſtrate the wiſdom and goodneſs of God to be alike infinite. For what but a moſt unparallel'd and ſtupendous clemency in ſuch a Son, could ever have qualified him to forgive (did I ſay) nay to forget, a like impiety againſt ſuch a Father! what but ſuch a Miracle of Magnanimity or Chriſtian patience in the one, could have pardoned even to <hi>Oblivion</hi> the guilt of thoſe who ſo eminently were ſelf-condemned by the <hi>Piety and Innocency</hi> of the other!</p>
            <p>A Royal temper indeed! enough at once to put us out of doubt why, or how 'tis <hi>ſaid</hi> that <hi>Kings are gods,</hi> and into doubt again, whether there be not a better <hi>medium</hi> of Government than <hi>Fear!</hi> whether the<note n="*" place="margin">Tacitè permittitur quod ſine ultione pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibetur. <hi>Tertul.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Fathers</hi> Aſſertion, that what is not <hi>congruouſly</hi> puniſhed is <hi>tacitly</hi> allowed, might
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62834:22"/>
not now be put to <hi>Problem</hi> in its own defence? And indeed were there as much <hi>force</hi> as there is <hi>reaſon</hi> in goodneſs to oblige, the doubt were over, there being nothing in the world that ſhould ſo reaſonably influence the minds of men as the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of <hi>kindneſs</hi> without the <hi>reaſon</hi> of <hi>merit,</hi> much more, againſt the reaſon of our demerits. But the corruption of humane <hi>nature</hi> being ſuch as ordinarily nouriſheth pride in our ſelves and malignity againſt goodneſs in others, it conſequently joyns enmity with ingratitude and perverſeneſs to diſobedience, whence it proves ſo very hazardous an experiment of ruling, as is thought worthy to be checkt by a Proverb, of <hi>killing with kindneſs;</hi> and therefore the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of all times has made it out of queſtion, that Laws would be no more than idle ludicrous things, if they were not dignified and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted by their ſanctions of rewards and puniſhments. However, if the Subjects of ſuch a Prince, would but give him the honour of his own <hi>mercy</hi> (which can never be well done but with the utmoſt of a grateful obedience) no good man would grutch them the benefit of the ſame: and if they ſhould do ſo ill as to preclude to themſelves <hi>this;</hi> yet let them not do worſe than ſo by denying their <hi>Prince that.</hi> Can we now not acknowledge the kindneſs of that <hi>Providence,</hi> which firſt gave us, then preſerved for us, and afterward reſtored to us ſuch a Prince as this, and all theſe in ſuch a manner; ſo ſignal and above ordinary courſe, by a <hi>Star</hi> at his Birth, by his eſcape at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and by his un-bloudy Reſtauration, when, as ill as we had us'd him, he was more deſired and wanted by the Nations than they could be by him?</p>
            <p>We cannot for our <hi>hearts</hi> deny, or if we could that, yet we cannot for our <hi>ſenſes</hi> but confeſs thoſe Teſtimonies God himſelf hath thus given of his pity and mercy towards us in the inſtance of this Monarch of mercy, and ſhall we dare to pervert our apprehenſions of this bleſſing into jealouſies and fears againſt him, inſtead of thankfulneſs to God for him, or make our experience of Gods gracious <hi>Providence</hi> in this <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion,</hi> a ground for <hi>doubting</hi> or <hi>ſhifting</hi> it in the <hi>next?</hi> God forbid.</p>
            <p>Let us never hope to proſper by iniquity, who are ſure we can never be miſerable without ſin. We know we may and how we may be happy in Suffering, with comfort and without guilt; yet neither ſo, nor ſo, when we ſuffer for our own ſakes and not for Gods, when we do againſt the command, that which is not righteous, that we may not ſuffer, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the command, for that which is. For as he ſaid, <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt ut eam non ut vivam,</hi> ſo we all know our <hi>Obedience</hi> is neceſſary, when our <hi>Security</hi> may not, and our <hi>reſiſtance</hi> cannot be ſo.</p>
            <p>He tells us now he will ſtep a while from the glaſs, and make room for our <hi>diſſenting</hi> brethren to come and ſee, and then tell us plainly,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62834:22"/>
whether what has been here repreſented, be not ſo there; and as the worſt he wiſhes to them is that what he hath ſeen or ſaid might be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial; ſo the beſt he can hope for them is that by their compliance with, (or rather than fail, their condeſcenſion to) their Superious, they will make it ſo. This, as it is the greateſt <hi>Charity</hi> he can <hi>have</hi> for them; ſo is it the <hi>leaſt</hi> as he ſaith, that for his own part he would <hi>uſe</hi> towards them. For that as long and as ſteddily as he hath been <hi>looking</hi> in this <hi>Glaſs,</hi> and among ſo many plain and evident <hi>rules</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> as he hath ſeen there, he cannot diſcern the leaſt ſhadow of <hi>ground</hi> or <hi>reaſon</hi> to juſtifie the <hi>making,</hi> or excuſe the <hi>maintaining</hi> their <hi>Separation;</hi> (but much, very much, to aggravate and condemn both) And therefore he warrantably concludes, that, abſtractly from <hi>Pride</hi> or <hi>Ignorance, Intereſt</hi> or <hi>Humour,</hi> there can be none. And therefore alſo he <hi>Conjures</hi> and <hi>Obteſts</hi> his brethren by the <hi>mercies</hi> of God; by the <hi>bowels</hi> of Chriſt; by the <hi>Indulgence</hi> of the King, and the <hi>Love</hi> of their Countrey; by the <hi>Honour</hi> of Religion, and the <hi>Bond</hi> of Nature; by the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of Law, and the <hi>Obligation</hi> of Conſcience; by the <hi>Guilt</hi> of their League, and the <hi>Debt</hi> of their Allegiance; by the <hi>Miſeries</hi> of the <hi>Firſt,</hi> and the <hi>Mercies</hi> of the <hi>Second CHARLES;</hi> by the <hi>Truth</hi> of their <hi>Repentance</hi> for the one, and <hi>Gratitude</hi> to the other; by the <hi>Grief</hi> and <hi>fear</hi> of their acknowledged brethren, and the <hi>Rage</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> of the common enemy; by the <hi>Memory</hi> of former, as the <hi>Fate</hi> of all future diſobedience; by the deareſt and moſt prevailing names, of <hi>Chriſtian-Catholick-Reformed-Proteſtant</hi> (and) <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men, they would now give us the <hi>right hand</hi> of <hi>Fellowſhip,</hi> and both hands of help and aſſiſtance, by an hearty compliance with, and ſubmiſſion to the moſt approved, equal, comely, Primitive and Apoſtolick Eſtabliſht Government, of this Confeſſedly <hi>True, Sound, Lawful, Reformed, Proteſtant CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH of ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:62834:23"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Henry Brome</hi>'s Advertiſement. 1680.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WHereas there are ſeveral Diſcourſes and Pamphlets abroad in the World, that paſs for the Writings of Mr.</hi> Roger L'Eſtrange; <hi>wherein he never had any hand at all; This is to Advertiſe the Reader, that he hath lately Publiſhed theſe following Pieces, (all but the Two laſt) and no other.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Toleration Diſcuſs'd, in a Dialogue betwixt a Conformiſt and a Non-Conformiſt, and betwixt a Presbyterian and an Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seneca</hi>'s Morals Abſtracted.</item>
               <item>The Guide to Eternity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tully</hi>'s Offices, in Engliſh.</item>
               <item>Twenty Select Colloquies of <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in Engliſh.</item>
               <item>Tyranny and Popery Lording it over the Conſciences and Lives of the King and People.</item>
               <item>The Reformed Catholick.</item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of the Plot in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Free-born Subject.</item>
               <item>The Caſe Put for the Duke of <hi>York.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Anſwer to the Appeal.</item>
               <item>Seaſonable Memorials.</item>
               <item>The Parallel, <hi>or</hi> The Growth of Knavery.</item>
               <item>A Dialogue betwixt a Citizen and Bumpkin.</item>
               <item>A Dialogue betwixt a Citizen and Bumpkin, the ſecond Part.</item>
               <item>A Further Diſcovery of the Plot, with a Letter to Dr. <hi>Titus Oates.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Gentleman Apothecary.</item>
               <item>Five Love-Letters Tranſlated.</item>
               <item>Diſcovery on Diſcovery, in a ſecond Letter to Dr. <hi>Titus Oates.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Committee, <hi>or,</hi> Popery in Maſquerade, curiouſly done in a Copper-Plate.</item>
               <item>The Way of Peace.</item>
               <item>The Arts and Pernicious Deſigns of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
